<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practise of the banckrupts of these times in whom are considered, 1. Their fraudulent and deceitfull actions. 2. The evills accompanying their courses. 3. Laws and punishments ordain'd to curbe them. 4. The charitable cure of so great an evill. A worke now very necessaary. Written in Latine by Mr Dainel Sauterius, and made to speake English for the generall good of all commerce.</title>
            <author>Sauter, Daniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837461</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11530)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1006:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practise of the banckrupts of these times in whom are considered, 1. Their fraudulent and deceitfull actions. 2. The evills accompanying their courses. 3. Laws and punishments ordain'd to curbe them. 4. The charitable cure of so great an evill. A worke now very necessaary. Written in Latine by Mr Dainel Sauterius, and made to speake English for the generall good of all commerce.</title>
                  <author>Sauter, Daniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 109 [i.e. 111], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Norton, for William Garret.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.DC.XL [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In four parts, each with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Pages 109 and 111 misnumbered 99 and 109.</note>
                  <note>Last numbered page: 109.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at head, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bankruptcy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRACTISE OF THE BANCKRVPTS OF THESE TIMES: In whom are conſidered,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Their fraudulent and deceitfull actions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The evills accompanying their courſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Laws and Puniſhments ordain'd to curbe them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>The charitable cure of ſo great an evill.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>A worke now very neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Written in Latine by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Daniel Sauterius,</hi> and made to ſpeake Engliſh for the generall good of all Commerce.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Norton,</hi> for <hi>William Garret. Anno</hi> M.DC.XL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE HONORABLE AND WORSHIPFULL: And all other of what degree ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who have occaſion to deale in any paſſages betweene Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors and Debtors, the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor wiſheth all happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable and Wor<hi rend="sup">ll</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am not ſo perverſly minded, as not to diſcerne, nor ſo ingratefull as not to acknowledge Gods great goodneſse to our Nation
<pb facs="tcp:1782:3"/>in granting and beſtowing on us, as all things needfull for our bodies, ſo alſo plentifull and neceſſary inſtructions for our ſoules. Yea I behold with much joy many of the Sages of our Law, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in place of Government, adding to their skill in the Laws of this Land, and promptneſſe in matters concerning mens temporall eſtates, the knowledge of Gods ſacred Book, and heavenly skill: as for the Salvation of their owne ſouls, ſo alſo for keeping others from unjuſt courſes prejudicing their eternall eſtate. I ſee this, I ſay, in many, I hope it in the reſt: hence therefore I am induced to preſent this Treatiſe to the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of all ſuch as love Gods ſacred truth, and be in place, and ſtrive to promote faithfull and juſt dealing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man: without which
<pb facs="tcp:1782:3"/>two, props the Commonwealth may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but will hardly finde true ſafetie. So that their endeavour is highly to be commended, who imploy their thoughts and paines in upholding the ſame. Subtle heads may deviſe, and worldly policie may forge many ſhifts; but juſtice armed with inſight into divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane lawes, will never, or not eaſily be deluded. Goe on therefore with noble and undanted reſolutions, ſhew your ſelves ſtill and ever men fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſse. By rooting out of the vice in this Book treated of, take away the blemiſh of Merchandiſe, the ſubverter of faire and juſt dealing, the bane of Widowes, and Orphanes and many others, the underminer of Iuſtice, the ſtaine of Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. So being faithfull in diſcharge of
<pb facs="tcp:1782:4"/>your places for a ſhort time here, God of his mercie and goodneſse will advance you to a place of endleſse bliſſe hereafter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:4"/>
            <head>To the moſt Noble, High and Prudent Counſellors of State in Holland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ncient writers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble the force of <hi>Muſick,</hi> have recorded, that it hath cured divers infirmities both of body and minde. How farre their relations may bee credited may not without cauſe be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned. But tis undoubtedly true, <hi>that the diſeaſes of mens minds have been and are often cured by pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, ſeaſonable admonitions, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full counſels, and religious directions.</hi> For to this end God hath given us his ſacred Scripture, that it might be a Cloſet and ſtore-houſe full
<pb facs="tcp:1782:5"/>fraught with medecines of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which the depravations of humane frailtie may be corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and men bee perſwaded (which God often inculcateth) <hi>to eſchew evill, and doe good.</hi> Having well weighed this with my ſelfe: I reſolved among other Eccleſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall performances of my calling, to attempt the cure of a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and pernitious ſore among tradeſmen: who by crafty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and ungodly courſes become Banckrupts
<hi>to the diſgrace of their calling, diſturbance of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, impoveriſhing of their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and the diſcredit</hi> (a thing much to be lamented) of
<hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> And ſurely much the worſe are the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of delinquents in this kinde,
<pb facs="tcp:1782:5"/>becauſe God of his eſpeciall favour hath given us plentifull know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and divine directions moſt cleere, to keep us in the wayes of God, and in honeſt, faithfull, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and Chriſtian dealing. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when I ſaw and conſidered the ill conſequents of Banckrupts naughty practiſes; I judged them more hurtfull and miſchievous, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their diſeaſes who are affected and afflicted with corporall mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of what kinde ſoever; for bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily diſeaſes eſpecially grieve the outward man of the partie diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; often conduce to the ſafety of the ſoule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereas the evils ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying Banckrupts proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, cauſe much detriment and harme to all ſuch as deale with
<pb facs="tcp:1782:6"/>them, and caſt the Banckrupts headlong into many ſinnes preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to their ſoules. Thence it is that often yee ſhall find Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts deafe to good counſell, lame and not able to tread in the pathes of equity; blinde, and not willing to ſee what belongeth to faire dealing. Men diſtracted, and ſuch as be infected with the plague, are ſhut up in cloſe places from doing miſchiefe: But banckrupts frequent Markets and places of Commerce, and by crafty &amp; cunning carriage wrong full many. Obſtructions in the veines may breed ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes in mens bodies; but the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and dealings of theſe craftie deceivers cauſe obſtructions and ſtoppage to all faithfull dealing &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1782:6"/>trading. Wherefore I have in brief, 1. <hi>Layd open the diſeaſes of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</hi> 2. <hi>Shewed the vices incident to them.</hi> 3. <hi>Declared what laws have bin enacted to prevent their evill dealings.</hi> 4. <hi>Vnfolded the remedies neceſſary for the cure thereof.</hi> And in each part of my diſcourſe intermingled pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wholſome exhortations, reproofs, admonitions out of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry learned &amp; approved authors; and with that moderation dealt with them, that if they rightly conſider of my Endeavours, they ſhall have more cauſe to embrace and like of this Treatiſe, than to maligne and reproach it. I am one among the reſt of <hi>Gods watch-men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exek.</hi> 3.17.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and ſeeing ſo manifeſt a miſchiefe bred, growing up, and increaſing,
<pb facs="tcp:1782:7"/>
               <hi>might not in any wiſe hold my peace.</hi> May it pleaſe you to accept of, and take into your patronage a worke ſo neceſſarie for the Credit and quietneſſe of a Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and the defence and protection of many Innocent and wronged Creditors. Thus pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to protect you under the ſhadow of his wings, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you in theſe troublſome times for the happy &amp; proſperous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of the charge committed to you, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe in all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an obſervance to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> Daniel Sauterius.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mart.</hi> 20. 1615.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:7"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wiſh from my heart (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that this Booke uſefull (as it ſeemeth) in other Countreyes, had been needleſſe in ours. So might I have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my labour in tranſlating it, and you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have imployed your time than in reading it. But ſuch is the frequency and obliquity of Banckrupt courſes at this day with us, that it was thought neceſſary to fetch theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes and Medicines for the ſame from our neighbors Countrey. And J knew not where better to finde them, than in this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author; who in this his diſcourſe hath ſpoken of this ſubject briefly, and yet uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, judiciouſly, religiouſly. Read it thorough, and ſeriouſly conſider each paſſage. No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous and well-minded peruſer hereof can chooſe but be bettered by it in his judgment,
<pb facs="tcp:1782:8"/>as, for the producing in his heart an hatred of this vice: ſo, for diſcerning the crafty wiles &amp; tricks of them, who will lay Harpyes claws on what they can catch, and part from nothing which poſsibly they can hold. Jt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe be, but that ſome perſons at ſight hereof will fret in their hearts, bend their brows, and ſowre their ſpeeches. I wiſh them a better temper, and more calme affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, &amp; ſuch a demeanor towards them, who minde their good, as may cleerely teſtify good ground of hope for their amendment. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Sauterius</hi> the religious and learned Author hereof, being a worthy and faithfull Watch-man of God, hath given warning of the evill in the world, which he ſaw to grow too rife and encreaſe exceeding much;<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Hee hath admoniſhed the wicked of his wicked way, and done what God his Maſter enjoyned him:</hi> It remaineth alſo that men doe their parts,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.21. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>And turne out of their evill wayes, that they may live.</hi> Jf there be any who notwithſtanding will run headlong on in their owne courſes and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent practiſes, to them J ſay; Goe too now
<pb facs="tcp:1782:8"/>yee falſe and deceitfull dealers: rejoyce in your advantages ſubtlily got, whilſt they which looſe by you, weep: Cloth your ſelves bravely, feed daintily, looke high, whilſt your Creditors goe with dejected Countenances, bee barely clad or naked, and want neceſſary food: Abound you in all jollity und earthly pleaſure, whilſt others groane under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſad miſeries, into which you have caſt them: But remember that for all theſe things God will bring you to Judgment. But I hope better things of you, and ſuch as tend to the future reformation of your courſes. I wiſh the intelligent and godly Reader to hope the ſame with me, and admoniſh all who have been ſubtle and fraudulent delinquents in the practiſes here ſpoken of, not to deceive us in our hopes, leaſt they deceive themſelves of their future comfort. More I ſhall not need to ſay, becauſe the religious Author hath very well opened his minde concerning this Treatiſe, and I have briefly compriſed it in the Epiſtle precedent.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1782:9"/>
            <head>THE PRACTISE OF THE BANCKRVPTS OF THESE TIMES.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>The firſt Part,</hi> Declaring their deceitfull actions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eathen writers of Old exclamed, O the Times!<note place="margin">A complaint of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the times.</note> O the courſes of men! O their wickedneſſe! For they ſaw an infinite and intolerable licentiouſnes raigning; they<note n="a" place="margin">Plin. Epiſt. 2.14.</note> ſaw the barres of ſhame, and baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe broken up, and audacious men da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to doe any thing, and running into extremity of ſin without meaſure or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.
<pb facs="tcp:1782:10"/>ſtraint. They obſerved<note n="b" place="margin">Juvenal. ſat. 13.</note> that there could be no bounds or limits ſet to mens ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, where an ingenuous bluſh was quite baniſhed from their hardned foreheads. They ſaw the market place full of buyers and ſellers, and plentie of Commerce, but ſaw likewiſe vices as frequent, as men. They beheld<note n="c" place="margin">Senec. of Auger. B. 2.</note> one man ſupplanting ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſcarce any man gayning but by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others loſſe, and ſome others for a little pleaſure or profit, not caring whom they ruinated; Then appeared alſo more wayes to ſin than means to reſtraine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and men ſtriving dayly, who ſhould outvie each other in miſchiefe. Then proneſſe to ſinne increaſed, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facedneſſe decreaſed: So that due reſpect to Authority and Juſtice being expelled, unbridled deſires ruſhed which way they luſted; Innocencie was rare, Vice frequent, and ſought not ſecrecy, but was ſo rooted in mens hearts that it feared not publick view.</p>
            <p>Theſe of old were the Heathens Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; and have not the ſtreames of vice from former times flowed down to us; and all later times made good, what our Saviour foretold of the dayes after him? Becauſe<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iniquitie ſhall be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1782:10"/>the Charity of many ſhall wax cold.</hi> Even now wee ſee, as it were a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounded to make a generall Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all men for the confounding of right and wrong. Now are benefits<note n="e" place="margin">Senec. B.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Benef.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited with miſchiefe, and men ſpare not to ſhed their blood for whoſe ſake they ought to venture their owne. In a word this was our Anceſtors complaint, this is ours; That<note n="f" place="margin">Id. B. 1. of Ben.</note> vertue is ſubverted, that vice raigneth, that all things grow worſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, and that the reines are let looſe to all impietie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That I may not ſeeme to be the Author of the Worlds defamation without juſt cauſe,<note place="margin">That matters grow worſe and worſe is proved by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Banckrupts.</note> a while examine with me the life and courſes of the men of theſe times. I wiſh they had not proceeded to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of injuſtice. Even now<note n="a" place="margin">As Lactant. of old B. 7. &amp; 15. of Div. reward.</note> Juſtice is rare; impietie, injurie, covetouſnes common; good men become a prey to the bad. There is no faithful dealing, no peace, no humanity, no ſhame, no truth;<note n="b" place="margin">Saluſt.</note> craft and ſubtle dealing is more prized than faithfulneſſe. This is moſt true in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Courſes of men. But eſpecially among Banckrupts; ſo that to defraud o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and leave trading, is no more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, than to goe from a Winter houſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1782:11"/>to a Summer houſe in May.</p>
            <p>As<note n="c" place="margin">Plaut. in Perſ.</note> eaſily doe ſome ſhift of their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, as a wheele in a ſwift race turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth round. What elſe is cauſe of theſe and the like evills, than a Corrupt Judgment of things? As namely, that<note n="d" place="margin">Proſperum ac felix ſcelus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us vocatur. Senec. Trag.</note> ſucceſſe in ill and fraudulent dealing maketh it counted a vertue.</p>
            <p>Becauſe their Craft proſpereth, even the ſucceſſe maketh a perverted Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thinke their ſinne warrantable; ſo that away they paſſe without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Then<note n="c" place="margin">Senec. B. 3. c. 10. of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefic.</note> alſo the multitude of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors taketh away the ſhame of the offence, and the Commonneſſe of the ill report maketh it ceaſe to be counted a diſgrace. So that hereby it<note n="f" place="margin">Dio. in Nerv.</note> cometh to paſſe, that we live in an age in which, I ſay not, a man may doe nothing, but in which a man may doe any thing. For now bad men become worſe by their good ſucceſſe, and pleaſe and delight themſelves, that the deſignes of their knavery<note n="g" place="margin">Salvian. of Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. B 1.</note> have a proſperous iſſue; ſuch are our times, our Courſes, our naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Concerning Banckrupts there are (for<note n="a" place="margin">Tull. de orat.</note> a right diſtinction of things beautifieth ſpeech,<note place="margin">Of two ſorts of Banckrupts</note> and preventeth objections) ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1782:11"/>kindes. The firſt is of them, who by caſualties have their ſubſtance waſted: The<note n="b" place="margin">Benven. in his Treatiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Banckrupts.</note> ſecond ſort are they, who by their owne default are impoveriſhed: Theſe laſt are the worſt ſort of men and deſerve no pitty. Of them I intend to ſpeake in due order. So that my ſpeech ſhall aime at no particular man, but make an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the vice in generall. Whoſoever therefore (as in like caſe <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ierom</hi> ſaith) ſhall be offended therewith, even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelfe in particular to be the man, who in generall is ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And firſt I will ſpeake of Banckrupts become ſo by Caſualties.<note place="margin">Of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts become ſo by Caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> The Lawyers ſay well; out<note n="a" place="margin">Sancinus de paen c. <hi>1.</hi> de injur. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> of a hatred to to the Guilty, to lay blame on the Guiltleſſe, is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to naturall equity. And tis thought altogether inhumane, that a Banckrupt ſhould be puniſhed, whoſe goods have been waſted by certain and evident ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties. Wherefore we cannot well lay the blame of his failing upon himſelfe, if it be made manifeſt, that he loſt not his goods by his own default.</p>
            <p>Now breaking of mens eſtates may befall, firſt by caſualties at Sea: when<note n="b" place="margin">Horat.</note> the Merchant by reſtleſſe paines (deſiring to fly povertie) ſay leth to the Indies, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1782:12"/>miſcarrying by ſtormes in his voyage becommeth poore. Wee<note n="c" place="margin">Tacitus ann.</note> all know that nothing ſubjects a man more to caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, than the Sea; and that<note n="d" place="margin">Senec ep, 36.</note> a Marchant needeth proſperous fayling, who ſhall ſtand to his ingagements: which if hee find not, he muſt needs be impoveriſhed, cannot pay his debts, and is compelled to leave the Exchange. 2. They<note n="c" place="margin">Benven. Treat. of Banckrupts.</note> may bee overthrowne by caſualties, who fall into Pirats hands: for Pirats<note n="f" place="margin">L. Florus B.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 6.</note> range and rob at Sea, hinder Commerce, ſhut up the Ports by their forces, and are worſe than a Tempeſt, ſo that no ſhip well fraight with wares of worth can paſſe them. And<note n="g" place="margin">Chryſoſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 4. on Gen.
1.</note> thereby often the Merchant becometh inſolvent, and departeth his Countrey. Laſtly, ſome men without their owne default, looſe their eſtates by being fraudulently dealt withall by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: So<note n="h" place="margin">2 K. 4. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eph. antiq. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> it befell the Prophets wife left in debt by her husband, not by her owne, but by anothers default; in this manner it may come to paſſe, that an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man may ſuffer through another mans fayling &amp; naughtineſſe. To become banckrupt abſolutely by another mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, is not lyable to infamy: and<note n="i" place="margin">Alex. of Alex. B. 5.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore queſtion need not be made concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1782:12"/>his corporall puniſhment. Hence, <hi>Otho</hi> made a law, that men impoveriſhed by Shipwrack, not by their owne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence or waſtfulneſſe, ſhould ſtand in an appointed publick place, that all men might ſee them, and out of true compaſſion relieve them. But whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpent themſelves by riotouſneſſe and ill courſes, ſhould be quite excluded and denyed that benefit. Now further conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we, what men undone by caſualties are to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When croſſes able to breake mens eſtates doe befall them and much trouble them, they ought not to fret and grieve,<note place="margin">What men undone by caſualties ought to doe.</note> but poſſeſſe their ſoules in patience. For<note n="a" place="margin">Cicer. ſam. ep. 8.</note> then is adverſitie patiently to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, when a man is not cauſe thereof. Well ſaid <hi>Cicero,</hi> common<note n="b" place="margin">Idem. fam. epiſt 5.</note> and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain caſualties which providence could not avoid, are wiſely to be ſuffered; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience leſſeneth not, but aggravateth greifs; whereas moderation<note n="c" place="margin">Plant. in Rudent.</note> of minde is like good ſawce, and ſweetneth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity. Let them therefore that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with croſſes, take unto themſelves a patient prudence, and learne to molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie hardſhip befalling them, with the skill of right learning adverſity. And let
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1782:13"/>them think, that this<note n="e" place="margin">Sence. ep. 103.</note> is one Haven of a ſea-toſſed &amp; troubled eſtate, to contemne chance, to ſtand boldly &amp; ward the darts caſt by croſſes with a reſolute heart pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them. Beſides, let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that they be men brought forth and ſubject to the common miſery of humane condition, and may not refuſe to live ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to that frailtie, to which men in this life are borne. Let them with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience undergoe the caſualties, which by any Councell, Prudence, and Providence they could not avoid, and remembring the croſſes, which have befallen others, think with themſelves, that no ſtrange, or uncouth, or unuſuall matter hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne and light upon them. Let them<note n="f" place="margin">Job 1.21. &amp;c. 10.</note> take <hi>Job</hi> for a patern of ſingular patience in manifold miſeries: So alſo <hi>Abraham</hi> a man conſpicuous both for croſſes, and happy ſucceſſe. With what evenneſſe of carriage, with what reſolution, did both theſe beare their troubles? In this manner all may be happy, who have learned by the courſe of human life well and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to beare miſerie, and not to ſhake off the yoke laid upon their necks. God the high and Almighty Governor of the world, permitteth croſſes to fall on men,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1782:13"/>yea layeth them on ſome: Not<note n="g" place="margin">Arrianus to Epict.
1.12.</note> out of a deſire to plague them, or to hurt them, but like a good Phyſitian, Tutor and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to doe them eſpeciall good. For we<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> know, that all things work together for good to them, that love God. Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 5.34.</note> brings forth patience, patience experience, experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed. If you deſire the furtherance of your owne Salvation: Heare what the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> 
               <hi>We are judged and chaſtiſed of the Lord, that wee ſhould not be condemned with the wicked world.</hi> Doth your faith languiſh? Croſſes aſſault you, that it may be rouzed up: God<note n="l" place="margin">Aug. in pſ. 93.</note> is good to you; for if he did not mixe ſome bitterneſſe amidſt the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this world, wee ſhould forget him. But by his raiſing ſtormes in mens mindes, by vexations and croſſes he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens faith, which before lay aſleep. Wherefore God by<note n="m" place="margin">Senec.</note> afflicting men out of fatherly good will to them, deſireth to put life into them, and to make them get new ſtrength. So that thoſe rather are truly to be called miſerable, who lie ſnorting in too much happineſſe, whom a lazie reſtineſſe poſſeſſeth, as in a becal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sea. Let us then think it beſt with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1782:14"/>patience to beare, what God pleaſeth to lay upon us: He ruleth as King, we muſt obey: Neither ſhall we ever be well prepared for croſſes, unleſſe without murmuring in the midſt of all troubles we can often ſay; <hi>Deo aliter viſum eſt, immo Deo melius quid viſum eſt:</hi> God hath a hand in this, yea, God hath laid this croſſe on me for my good: He knew what was beſt for me. Our minds being thus compoſed, will moderately and thankfully entertain happineſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and conſtantly beare adverſity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Further to comfort the former ſort of Banckrupts,<note place="margin">Of the ſecond ſort of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, who fall by their owne default.</note> ſhall not here be requiſite; becauſe our intent is not to treate of them: Come we to the ſecond kinde of Banckrupts who are<note n="a" place="margin">Benvent in his Treatiſe of Banckrupts.</note> impoveriſhed by their owne default, and are indeed the worſt ſort of men, worthy of no commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration; for their il cariage maketh them uncapable of pitie. Hence firſt antiently they were counted contemptible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous. This we ſee by <hi>Craſſus</hi> called the Rich<note n="b" place="margin">Val. Max. B. 11.</note>: His poverty in the end put on him the name of Banckrupt; for his goods (becauſe he could not make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Creditors) were ſold and himſelfe walking, as a begger, ſaluted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1782:14"/>with the bitter geere; Behold rich <hi>Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> Secondly, they were forbidden commerce. The 12 Roman tables ſay thus: <hi>Becauſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Jul. Paulus ſentent. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>you laviſh out your eſtates, we therefore forbid you the uſe of money and Commerce.</hi> Thirdly, they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged unworthy of the name of Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: for he that trades<note n="d" place="margin">Baldus in Genſ. 74.</note> unjuſtly or is an ill Tradeſman, is not properly called a Tradeſman, but equivocally and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively. Fourthly, becauſe not obſerving the rules of fidelity, they deſerve the ſtile of frandulent waſters of other mens mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and in<note n="e" place="margin">Benvent. in Treat. of Banckrupts.</note> Latin are called <hi>Decoctores;</hi> which word cometh from <hi>decoquo</hi> to boyle away; for as fire by little and little boyleth away the ſubſtance of any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor: ſo theſe Banckrupts by degrees waſte and diminiſh their eſtate. Fifthly, in
<hi>Tuſcany</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Boerius b. 7. Diviſ. 215.</note> and all Italy, they are called <hi>Banccafalliti,</hi> and in divers other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes Banckrupts, becauſe they faile, breake, and appeare not at the banck, table, or compting bord, where they ſhould pay their debts.</p>
            <p>Of theſe let us ſpeak in order, for (as <hi>Cicero</hi>) tis not enough to finde out and declare any thing: the maine matter is judiciouſly and orderly to intreate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1782:15"/>Concerning this ſort of Banckrupts firſt we will unfold their deceipts in getting other mens money into their poſſeſſion. Secondly, we will deſcribe their divers courſes of waſting it. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we will lay open their baſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt purpoſe to deceive and faile their Creditors.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Humane corruption<note n="a" place="margin">Plaut. in Rud.</note> hath deviſed many tricks and ſnares to deceive the unwary.<note place="margin">Of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts crafty courſes to get money into their poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Fowlers houſes are not more full of engines to catch birds, and fill their cages; than Banckrupts heads are full of plots to ſtore their warehouſes<note n="b" place="margin">Ariſtophan.</note>; Nor herein onely doe they deale craftily, but alſo diſhoneſtly, and knaviſhly. Gaine is the marke they aime at; which if<note n="c" place="margin">Lactant. B. 1. of true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> they cannot attaine by their lawfull trading, a falſe finger muſt doe the deed; they will cheate, ſteale, ſpoile, circumvent, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, ſtick at nothing; ſo that they may glitter in brave apparell, rings, pearles, and make a gallant ſhew with their ſilver and gold, and ſatisfy their greedie deſires with other mens wealth. Their firſt trick is pretending themſelves to be rich; for<note n="d" place="margin">Proverb. 15.</note> there is (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) one that maketh himſelfe rich, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he hath nothing: Theſe Banckrupts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1782:15"/>will make a ſhew as if they were Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, brave and accompliſhed Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Traders, both by their words and courſes, though they be of meane eſtate. Secondly, they conceit that brave apparell, orient Pearles, gold Chaynes, and the like gallantry will eaſily beguile the common people, who judge<note n="e" place="margin">Cicer. Orar. pro Roſe.</note> much from a light opinion, little from reall truth. Whence the report of their wealth ſhall be ſo blaſoned, that there can be no better birdlime for their buſh. Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh<note n="f" place="margin">Bernard B. 4. ad Eugen.</note> them of carrying a lower ſayle; Tuſh ſay they, I ſcorne it: It becometh me not: Tis not ſuteable for the time, this lofty carriage is for my good. Thirdly, to gaine the peoples applauſe, they build ſtately houſes, aſtoniſhing the beholders with their ſtrange Architecture the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way (ſaith <hi>Livie</hi>) to make rich men run much into other mens debts: So that 'tis a vanity of fooles and mad men, to gaine popular applauſe, and to make a nine dayes wonder for to get an opinion of their worth in mens minds, which ſoone fadeth, dyeth and deceiveth them. For what<note n="g" place="margin">Lactant. B. of true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip 11.</note> is it to pretend large poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to be much ingaged for them? to have brave houſes, but built with other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1782:16"/>mens money? to have gallant attendance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to want means anſwerable? Thoſe are ill accomptants, who ſee not that having paid their Creditors, they are juſt worth nothing; a Cipher may ſerve inſteed of <hi>ſumma totalis.</hi> The tongues of Banckrupts drop<note n="h" place="margin">Plaut. in Trucul.</note> milk and hony, when their hearts are fraight with Gall and Vinegar. They ſweeten<note n="i" place="margin">Lucret. B. 1.</note> the lip of the cup with ſweet juyce, when the potion is wormwood; and guild the pill and cover the diſtaſtfull Aloes, not to doe good, as loving Mothers and skilfull Phyſitians are wont, but to wipe<note n="k" place="margin">Plaut in Perſ.</note> men of their money with a few faire words, and cloſely and covertly to purloin o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens eſtates. Many more are the tricks and ſhifts of theſe deceivers: So that had I <hi>Centum linguas, oraque centum,</hi> an hundred mouthes and tongues, yet could I: not rehearſe the names of their tricks and legerdemain, much leſſe fully decipher them;<note place="margin">What Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts do, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got money into their clutches.</note> Let us further proceed to open them as well we may.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> When once Banckrupts have purſed the Coyne, not long after there is little hope of making paiment; their hands are lime-twigs, what once<note n="a" place="margin">Manus arripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae nunquam postea cripidae Plaut in Perſ.</note> they lay hold on, they never let goe. If you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1782:16"/>what is due, and require reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the money lent. 1. They have in their mouthes <hi>Antigonus</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Plutarch in the life of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his large promiſes; but as <hi>Chares</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> they will pay nothing. 2. If you urge and preſſe them to ſatisfie at the time<note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 29 4.</note> appointed, they deſire forbearance a while, they faine excuſes, plead hardneſſe of the times. 3. If more and more you be inſtant with them; Then they<note n="e" place="margin">Teren in Andria.</note> who could not at firſt deny payment, now when the time of performance is come, they muſt needs ſhew themſelves and deny it; and then moſt impudently they ſay; what are you? what would you have me doe? will you begger me and mine? I love you, but I muſt love my ſelfe better. But aske them; Is this your performance, is this your fidelity? they are not a ſhamed at all. At the borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where they ſhould be baſhfull and timerous, leſt they ſhould not be able to pay, ſhame was farre from them: Now when they ſhould pay, they feare, they bluſh, hide themſelves, which they ſhould not doe:
4. If you threaten to bring them before the Judge, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter and ſowre their ſpeech, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and geſture towards you, and with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1782:17"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1782:17"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1782:18"/>opprobrious and diſgracefull words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile you. The<note n="f" place="margin">Plaut in Cap.</note> greateſt part of men are of this temper. They are kinde and good till they obtaine their deſire; when they have obtained what they would, then become they ſtarke nought and extreme fraudulent. Theſe (as <hi>Siracides</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Eccleſ 29.5.</note> ſaith) till they receive what they deſire, kiſſe their neighbors hand, and humble their voice, and at laſt pay him with curſing and rebuke, and give him evill words for his good deeds:<note n="h" place="margin">Lyfias in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. B. 13.</note> for they reckon the money. which was but lent them, as a thing found, and conceit that which was lent them to uſe, as truly their own, as their patrimony rightly deſcended upon them. An utter evill kinde of men are theſe! may you not well affirme that there is leſſe danger in a ſtorme in the Iriſh Sea, than to deale with them? Let us ſee how they bring themſelves into theſe evills.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Tis no wonder that theſe Banckrupts have no fidelity,<note place="margin">The courſes of Banckrupts for ſpending their own and other mens eſtates.</note> nor care of reſtitution; for they obſerve no meane, no ſtint in ſpending, many wayes they laviſh out their eſtate. Firſt, by prodigall and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh largeſſe, not out<note n="a" place="margin">Cicero. offic. 1.</note> of a bountifull nature, but vaine glory, and to expend
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1782:18"/>more than their eſtare will be are, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippn</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Joſeph. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu. 18.8.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> the greats Nephew, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering himſelfe thereby. Or ſecondly, theſe Banckrupts ſpend all in riotous and exceſſive cheere, as the <hi>Eroliant</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Polyb. 13.</note> who plunged themſelves into debt by their delicious fare. or Thirdly, at gaming houſes take a compendious way to looſe all, imitating <hi>Claudius Caſor,</hi> who<note n="d" place="margin">Sueton.</note> was a moſt ſtudious gameſter, &amp; wrote a booke of the Art of gaming. Or fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as
<hi>Pericles</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Plutare. in Pericl.</note> the Athenian, by can gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent building which either ſhall have a ſhort or no continuance whereon to creat their memorie: This<note n="f" place="margin">Lactant. B. or true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip 6.11.</note> alſo is a ready vaine of needleſſe expence to ſquander a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the patrimony of light-heads. Or fifthly, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume their goods by giving themſelves up to luxurious<note n="g" place="margin">Florus
3.12.</note> preparation of magnificent banquets; which ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mother will ere long bring forth poverty a bare and needy daughter: for hereby may bee exhauted<note n="h" place="margin">Tacit. B 2.</note> a Princes treaſure: hereby the <hi>Boetians</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Polyb. B.
10.</note> after the <hi>Leuiruh</hi> battaill conſumed their wealth, and proved befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unkards. In <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> time there were found ſome, who<note n="k" place="margin">2. ag. Catil.</note> ſpent all their induſtrie and whole life in nightly revells: And after his dayes
<pb facs="tcp:1782:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1782:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1782:20"/>there aroſe others, who by<note n="l" place="margin">Benvent in Treat. of Banckrupts.</note> ſumptuous banquets and gluttony loſt both wit and wealth together. Such are ſtill living, and are the waſtfull brood and ſucceſſors of thoſe riotous and ſpend-all Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and predeceſſors. From theſe cauſes have iſſued ſuch abundance of inſolvent debtors.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               <note place="margin">The purpoſe of Banckrupts to run their Countreys or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceale them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note> We ſee alſo many now adayes as deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingaged as the Roman Knight,<note n="a" place="margin">Macrob. ſat. B. a. ch. 4.</note> to walk up and downe idle and heartleſſe, and not unlike to <hi>Annius</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Plin. B. 36. ch. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Milo,</hi> who did owe 700 Seſterties, and by <hi>Plinie</hi> is cenſured, as a Prodigie among men: Or as <hi>C. Curio</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Val. Max.</note>, who was ingaged for 600 Seſterties: Such men conceit it their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſe with
<hi>C. Galba</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Sueton.</note> the brother of <hi>Sergius</hi> the Emperor, as they have run out of their eſtates, ſo to run out of their countreyes. Wee need not ſeek far for domeſtick examples equalling the worſt of theſe, and never minding to pay their debts whilſt they live, and therefore to their great ignominie and diſgrace, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtly doe they purpoſe to fly their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive countrey, or play leaſt in ſight and mew themſelves up from their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors aſpect: And ſo to lye cloſe for a time, till compact can be made with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1782:20"/>their Creditors, to take part for their whole debt.<note n="e" place="margin">Minſing Inſt. 4.6.</note> So that they may be juſtly called, not onely
<hi>Forifugae</hi> Runagates from the market, but <hi>Lucifugae</hi> Runa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates from the ſight of men, and are termed by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pandect. 21.</note> night birds and batts: who in reſpect of their ingagements in the day lurke unſeene at home, and leſt they ſhould be caught by their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſcout forth in the night. I cannot but mourne for their naughtineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it little moveth themſelves. Oh their blindneſſe juſtly to be bewayled! For who is<note n="g" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> more miſerable than a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable man, who is unſenſible of his own miſerie? Charity ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> moveth me<note n="h" place="margin">Bernard. Epiſt 2.</note> to grieve for them, who being in a grievous eſtate, grieve not for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; yea it maketh me the rather to pitty them, becauſe when their caſe is pitifull, they perſwade not themſelves in how pitifull a condition they are. Well, let us proceed in this diſcourſe. Plenty of matter afforded carrieth us on further and forbiddeth us here to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1782:21"/>
            <head>THE PRACTISE OF THE BANCKRVPTS OF THESE TIMES.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Part,</hi> Shewing the Evils incident to Banckrupts.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Many evills proceed from the fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dealing of banckrupts.</note> BUt what? me thinks I heare the Banckrupt within himſelfe ſay: The rude rable of the people geere and hiſſe at me, but I applaud my ſelfe at home when I view the baggs in my cheſt;<note n="a" place="margin">As Horacea ſat. 1. Serm. 1.</note> what need I care, what my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours chat: when as I know, how by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens miſeries and griefe to get a goodly and rich prey for my ſelfe? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with this impudent ſpeech. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Tully</hi> could<note n="b" place="margin">Book 3. of offic.</note> cenſure it for a crime
<pb facs="tcp:1782:21"/>of wicked men, that any thing ſhould ſeeme good and profitable for them, which is not alſo juſt, honeſt, and may ſtand with their credit. Undoubtedly in theſe our times tis much to be lamented, that men out of an opinion of things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their good, that is, their profit and advancing their eſtates, ruſh head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into many evils, if not into their owne perdition. Now that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and withdraw Banckrupts, who are deepeſt in this bad opinion, from their ill courſes: Let us conſider the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, confluence, and ſinck of evills iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing from their enormous courſes. Yea there is an Ocean of them; may you pleaſe with me compendiouſly to ſaile through them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt evill of Banckrupts. They diſturbe the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note> Many things there bee troublous to Commonwealths, pernicious to Cities and Kingdomes; but nothing worſe than the courſes of fraudulent waſters of their eſtates. For as the Sea is calme of its owne nature, but made dangerous by violent winds: So a ſtate quiet in it ſelfe, is made ſubject to moſt violent tempeſts by the actions of fraudulent dealers. For they preferring their owne gaine before the publick good, diſquiet
<pb facs="tcp:1782:22"/>and diſturbe the commonwealth. This is evident. Firſt, becauſe fidelity in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Covenants and Promiſes is one maine foundation of a well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Commonwealth. Nothing ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Offic. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> doth more keep a State in due courſe, than fidelity in dealing, which is utterly taken away if there be not a faithfull and true payment made to Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors. If Banckrupts the Arch-builders of fraud, utterly ſubvert and take this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as indeed they doe, who doubteth<note n="b" place="margin">Bodin of the Com. W. B.
5.</note> but that the Commonwealth, unleſſe prevention be in time uſed, will ſhortly be ruinated? Secondly, by Banckrupts courſes, Trading which<note n="c" place="margin">Cicer. offic.
1.</note> was invented for the maintenance of the life of man, is quite overthrowne: yea commerce and dealing of man with man is the bond and prop of Cities and Kingdomes: If then Banckrupts weaken or violate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of fidelity, which to doe ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rhet. to Theod. 1.15.</note> overthroweth all uſe of trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among men: The Commonwealth cannot floriſh, but become a body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſoule. Thirdly, often ſeditions and &amp; diſcords ariſe upon Banckrupts cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Creditors of their eſtates, or Compounding with them for the third
<pb facs="tcp:1782:22"/>or fourth part. <hi>Tully</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Bodin of the Com. W.
5.11.</note> cenſured that the cancelling the firſt Covenants made with the Creditors, and drawing new Covenants is the overthrow of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a State. And <hi>Seneca</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Caelius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. 12.10.</note> ſaith, that the benefit of new Compounding is moſt pernitious to a Commonwealth. And ſurely no leſſe miſchiefe cometh to a Citty by giving liberty to Banckrupts to abide inſolvent; for hereby a greater occaſion<note n="g" place="margin">Bodin. 5.11.</note> is afforded deſperate men to violate their promiſes and Covenants, and to diſquiet all. And truly this will be the Condition of our times, unleſſe ſpeedily a remedy be applyed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this miſchief ſpreading in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of the Commonwealth; leſt<note n="h" place="margin">Por. Lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Catil.</note> as a flame at length it ſo prevaile, that it lay hold on all (which God Almighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) and we in vaine goe about to quench the furious and exorbitant flames thereof.<note place="margin">The ſecond evil of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the Actions of Banckrupts, perjury hath its place: If<note n="a" place="margin">Salvian. B. 3. of Gods go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> fraud and perjurie be incident to the courſes of ill trading, much more to the courſes of Banckrupts by whom no courſe is<note n="b" place="margin">Sophocl.</note> counted ill, which may make for their gaine: Thence goe they on to the Carthaginian<note n="c" place="margin">Cic. B. 1. of the Punick. W.</note> perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:1782:23"/>and obſerve no true, no holy dealing, and ſo familiarly<note n="d" place="margin">Plaut. Bragg. ſould.</note> uſe falſe ſpeech, falſe deeds, falſe ſwearing, and play faſt and looſe at pleaſure: 'Tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, tis not agreed; 'Tis not agreed, 'tis agreed; And<note n="f" place="margin">Alex. of Alex. B. 5. C. 10.</note> think they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive men with falſe oathes, as Children with Toyes: When they borrow they Covenant, plight their troth, make mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall promiſe of performance, doe it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their owne hand writing, have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſubſcribed thereunto. But what of all this? They<note n="g" place="margin">Ariſtoph.</note> (as <hi>Eucrates</hi>) have a way and trick to fruſtrate all this; they can ever finde a ſtarting hole, a ſleight to avoid all, and neglect all fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity. Firſt, Put them in minde of their promiſe, preſſe them to fidelity. They ſtick not to ſay by their practiſe, if faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealing<note n="h" place="margin">Sueton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> be to be violated, it is to be done (not as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid for a Kingdome, but for a leſſe matter) for money. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions be pious. Yea they are like luſtful lovers, who<note n="i" place="margin">Catul.</note> feare not to ſweare, to promiſe any thing; but when their luſt is ſatisfied, they neither feare, nor care what they ſaid, or what they ſwore. Secondly, if their owne hand writing cannot hold them, no marveil that their<note n="e" place="margin">Plaut Aulul.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1782:23"/>words cannot. Their<note n="k" place="margin">Juvenal. ſat. 16.</note> owne ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their ſeale of a rich Pearle kept in an Ivory box, cannot make them to pay the money borrowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vana ſupervacuae dicunt chirographa chartae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The evidence produced is but a ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led paper in their accompt; they will rather part with all ſhamefaſtneſſe, than a dram of ſilver, and therefore eſteeme<note n="l" place="margin">Cic.</note> witneſſes a ſport, and an oath as a jeſt. Filthineſſe added to deformity cauſeth the greater loathing in the body: Now how great is the corruption and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a perjured and depraved ſoule? Whither<note n="m" place="margin">As Enn. in Cic. offic.</note> now is reaſon, which uſed to ſtand upright, unreaſonably bowed and inclined? Is there no puniſhment<note n="n" place="margin">Juvenal. ſat. 13.</note> in ſtore for perjured tongues and ſubtle fraud? Poore Soules! Though<note n="o" place="margin">Tibul.</note> for a time yee may eſcape: at length Revenge cometh with ſtill and ſlow, yet with ſure ſtepps; yee cannot avoid it.</p>
            <p>The third evill obſervable, in Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts is breach of brotherly love and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:<note place="margin">Thirdly, Banckrupts break the bonds of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love and charity.</note> For Banckrupts poſſeſſing and waſting other mens goods, cannot chuſe but breake the bands of humane friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and charity, which forbids<note n="a" place="margin">Cic. offic. 1.</note> to

<pb facs="tcp:1782:24"/>wrong any man, and injoynes us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the common good, and by mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all interchange of duties, and truſting forth and receiving againe wares, to confirme the bands of humane ſociety.<note place="margin">Cic. offic. 3.</note> Theſe bonds will not Banckrupts ſpare to breake; and therefore alſo undermine the very foundation of humane ſociety, to inrich themſelves and others with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens money and eſtates. Lend any thing<note n="c" place="margin">In Trinum.</note> (ſaith one in <hi>Plautus</hi>) thou looſeſt it: the borrower taketh it as his owne: aske it againe, for thy good will thou findeſt the borrower thine enemy: preſſe to reſtitution, and then, of two evils take thy choiſe, either to looſe what was lent, or elſe thy friend. They will neglect the bond of friendſhip and not pay. <hi>M. Craſſus</hi> was at once berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note n="d" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> both of money and friends: for when at the time appointed he craved to receive what he lent without uſe: that which was done by him <hi>gratis</hi> was more odious to them than had he lent it upon uſe; Thus made he of friends, enemies, and for his money poſſeſſed the winde. O wretched men! who once thruſt out at dores fidelity and friendſhip, who are ſo averſe from faire dealing, that they
<pb facs="tcp:1782:24"/>carry a violent hate and hoſtile rancor towards their Creditors, and opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſeek to diſgrace them! Give me leave to exclame and powre out this juſt Complaint. <hi>The good man</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mic. 7.2.</note> 
               <hi>is periſhed from the earth, there is none righteous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: They all lye in waite for blood, every one lyeth in waite for his brother with a net.</hi> 'Tis ſafer truſting to fire and water than to fraudulent men: 'Tis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer<note n="f" place="margin">Crates in Lactant.</note> to doe a kindneſſe to a ſerpent or ſavage beaſt by breeding them up, than to theſe men. What more harmefull, what more cruell to man, than the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, Panther, Lyon?<note place="margin">Elian. T B. 13.</note> yet did a Dragon preſerve from theeves a Youth who had accuſtomed to feed him. The Panther,<note place="margin">Joh. a S. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. B. 5.</note> if a man free her young ones from the trap that hath caught them, fawneth on him and conducts him ſafe out of the deſert. A Lyon<note n="i" place="margin">Agell. 5.14.</note> requited <hi>Androdus</hi> for pulling the ſtump of a tree out of his foot, and defended him in the den of wilde beaſts, into which he was caſt at Rome, and thus ſhewed a gratefull memory of the cure wrought on him. And ſhall men with evill requite a kindneſſe done by lending them money? Truly it is not ſafe to<note n="k" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> bring up ſavage creatures, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:1782:25"/>mindes are ſoone alienated from their benefactors, and that to their great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill: becauſe they harme their maſters and requite with miſchiefe the kindnes done to them. Much more is it not ſafe to credit them with money, who will make a prey of it, and from a kindneſſe done them, raiſe extreme hoſtility and hatred,<note place="margin">Cic. offic.
3.</note> and in mens ſhapes expreſſe the ſavageneſſe of beaſts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fourthly, the theft of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</note> The Courſes of Banckrupts in the fourth place draw them within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of theft. If <hi>Cato</hi> likened<note n="a" place="margin">Advertiſ. ſur divers crimes.</note> a Uſurer (one of thoſe who in their times had no bounds ſet for their Conſideration) to a cloſe murtherer; ſurely a man may wel call a fraudulent Banckrupt a thiefe; for of a ſet purpoſe he poſſeſſeth himſelfe of a Creditors eſtate, carrieth it away, and cheates him of it by cunning and ſubtle deviſes. This is thus proved: Firſt, if he according to <hi>Dracos</hi> lawes<note n="b" place="margin">Agell.
7.16.</note> be liable to theft, who imployeth a labouring beaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> otherwiſe than in that uſe for which he was let out to him: on the ſame ground are not Banckrupts, who uſe mens money to other uſes than they were lent, well termed theeves? Now they turne them to other uſes than the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1782:25"/>lender intended, 1. when they laviſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out upon their pleaſures. Secondly, when they borrow them of one Creditor to ſtop another Creditors mouth, that cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours againſt them. Such<note n="c" place="margin">Diodorus 16.</note> was the fault of the
<hi>Phocians,</hi> who to pay the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercement to the <hi>Amphictyons,</hi> conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to rob the Delphick Temple. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when Banckrupts ſpend the borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note n="d" place="margin">Henry 4. K. of France E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. An. 1605.</note> money in eſtating their Sonnes or making rich dowries for their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or any way convey and turne them over to their heires or agents or friends in truſt: Thus ſome Banckrupt doth, though it be a folly in him to provide for others, and be in want himſelfe, or to make others unjuſtly to gape after his death and wealth, who unjuſtly rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed others of it: for oftentimes the<note n="e" place="margin">Senec. Epiſt.</note> largeneſſe of the prey and intire enjoying it, maketh them of friends turne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Banckrupt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Banckrupts are proved ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to theft thus; if by all mens verdict he be judged a thiefe, that having pawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or lent on conſideration any thing, takes it cloſely into his poſſeſſion before the time; much more is he to be accuſed of theft, who after the time of payment
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1782:26"/>is expired, deteineth in his hand another mans money againſt the owners minde, and will not reſtore it. The former is true; for by his own conſent to lend it, he made the uſe of the thing another mans if therefore he take it away before the ſet time, he endammageth the borrower and committeth theft, as ſay the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers. <hi>L. Si quis cui. D. de furto L. in actione * qui rem &amp; L. ſi aves D. de furtis,</hi> therefore alſo the latter is true.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he is a thiefe that concealeth another mans goods: But Banckrupts often conceale borrowed money, and will not let their Creditors know their eſtates; and running away with all or a good part thereof, ſay that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent. And ſurely in all paſſages, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in concealing of goods got into their hands, ſo many and ſo covert are Banckrupts ſubtilties that they cannot be either unfolded or indeed imagined. In ſo much, that 'tis taken for granted among Lawyers, That<note n="f" place="margin">Nic. Boerius.</note> Banckrupts and fugitive merchants or tradeſmen may be wracked, that they may tell what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the money lent them for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize and trading, which now they deny themſelves to have, and ſay, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1782:26"/>the Retayler hath got it, and by him it is loſt: Therefore for concealment of other mens goods they may have theeft layd to their charge.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, he<note n="g" place="margin">Danaeus in his Ethic Lev. 19.12. Exod.
22.17.</note> committs theft, who denyeth what he borrowed or had depoſited in his hands: But banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts often deny with impudent faces that they received the money which was lent them; therefore they are liable to bee accuſed of theft. Now to deny the truth in this kinde is baſe and diſhoneſt, and maketh a man uncapable of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of avoiding priſon and compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Creditors.</p>
            <p>Beſides 'tis no ingenuous part,<note place="margin">Minſing Inſt. b. 4.</note> rather to bee found in the crime of theft, than to pay what a man oweth: And if they be men of place, they ſhould regard what beſeemed their perſons; for it is more groſſe and baſe for men in dignity to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent by fraud, than to take goods from others by open force and violence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fifthly, Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts guilty of murther.</note> Greater yet is the miſchief ariſing from the dealing of Banckrupts: For fifthly, they are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo guilty of murther. For firſt, there is in them an intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to hurt and wrong others in the courſe of their lives. And as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1782:27"/>ſaith, every unjuſt motion<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. in Johan.</note> of the minde, by which men are incited to to wrong their brother, is murther. Thus are they mutherers not armed with ſwords, but with fraud and craft for their owne gaine to overthrow others. Secondly, he that depriveth others of the neceſſaries for their life, what doth he elſe but deprive them of their lives? He killeth<note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 34
22.</note> his neighbour, that taketh his bread from him; he that<note n="c" place="margin">Tull. offic 1.</note> unjuſtly ſetteth upon another with craft to wrong him, doth as it were lay violent hands on him. If Banckrupts by their Cunning ſhifts and tricks carry away the money of honeſt Cittizens, poore wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and Orphanes, which ſhould ſuſteyne their lives, what doe they elſe but as Vultures ſuck their blood and teare in peeces, and devoure them who are innocent, and know not how to help themſelves?</p>
            <p>But the Banckrupts plead, doe we not for their money afford unto them the yearely maintenance, upon which they live? I anſwer, this ſmall kindneſſe is ſoone turned into a great miſchiefe: Nor indeed is it a kindneſſe, to ſeeme to doe Creditors good for a while, and then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1782:27"/>wholly to rob them. So then thirdly, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſhew of being helpfull to Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors lives, the Banckrupts in the end goe away with the principall, and dig the deeper pit for their Creditors over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. This kindneſſe of Banckrupts is like the ſtinging of the Aſpe, with whoſe<note n="d" place="margin">Chryſoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hom.</note> venome if a man be infected, he falleth in a pleaſing ſleep, ſo that the venome diſperſeth it ſelfe through all the veines, and the party dieth ſweetly ſleeping: So the Banckrupt for a while lulleth with kinde ſupply his Creditor aſleep, that he may diſperſe his poyſon more ſecurely, and carry away the principall, and by ſpoyling<note n="e" place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> him of his lively hood doth prejudice to his life; ſo that Banckrupts may be juſtly called a viperous brood, who eate out the very bowells and the ſtates of their Creditors, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may ſubſiſt in the world. What difference<note n="f" place="margin">Senec. B. of Benef.</note> then is there betweene a Banckrupts kindneſſe and an enemies wiſh? an enemie wiſheth thy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and a Banckrupt by pretending to ſupply thy life with maintenance, in the end worketh thy ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sixtly, Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> Furthermore the courſes of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts are in the ſixt place full of craft and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1782:28"/>cannot want hypocriſie: Doe<note n="a" place="margin">Plaut in Pſeud.</note> but heare their humble words &amp; view their ſmooth faces, no man can think them bad men, <hi>at opera fallunt,</hi> you ſhall find them falſe in their deeds, like<note n="b" place="margin">Baſil. Hom. 7 on Ex.</note> the fiſh called <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> which by taking the Colour of the rock by which it lieth, devours fiſhes approaching for ſhelter. So Banckrupts by taking and counterfeiting the colour of kinde and good men, make ſuch as come neere them their prey.</p>
            <p>Firſt then before they break they<note n="c" place="margin">Accurs in Benvent.</note> get ſtore of money into their hands, that they may ſeeme rich and able eaſily to ſatisfie their Creditors, ſo that no man needeth to preſſe them? And for this end, they will diſcharge other mens<note n="d" place="margin">Benvent in Tract. de Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto.</note> ingagments, that they may ſeeme ſome body, and good pay-maſters.</p>
            <p>Secondly, at their very breaking they play the hypocrites, and perfidiouſly blame the perfidiouſneſſe of fortune, and faine Caſualties, that they may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with their Creditors to their loſſe; yea they will pretend poverty and dammages, when they ſwim<note n="f" place="margin">Senec. of Ben. B. 4.</note> in plenty and have money coming in very fluſh; and to bring their Creditors to pity them, they can command ſome feined teares to diſtill.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1782:28"/>
            <p>Thirdly, after their breaking they conceive<note n="g" place="margin">Cic. orat. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his rec.</note> that all their vices are hid, if they but ſhew their faces in open mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket: and becauſe they beare wittingly<note n="h" place="margin">Lactan.</note> with their owne vices, whoſe ſweetnes much pleaſeth them, will not endure to have them named, but<note n="i" place="margin">Salvian.</note> make ſhew of religiouſnes and aſſume the title of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, that they may colour their diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt gaines and baſe ſhuffling dealings. Though their dealing be naught, yet they deſire to ſeeme of honeſt and faire carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; So deceitfull is mans life, ſo carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth be his minde in Covert, and ſetteth a faire face on a falſe heart; and thinks not, that<note n="k" place="margin">Cic. offic. 1.</note> there is no ſinne more capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and miſchievous for men, when they moſt notoriouſly beguile, even then to make the greateſt ſhew of honeſty. And ſurely herein is an by pocrite moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, becauſe hee<note n="l" place="margin">Cic.</note> catcheth and intrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth men, before they perceive any thing or can be aware. And therein<note n="m" place="margin">Plutarch of Herodor. Mal.</note> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the extremity of their injuſtice, that they would ſeeme juſt and honeſt, when they are not ſo; Secondly, their arrant naughtineſſe, that they counterfeit plaine dealing and goodneſſe, when they are moſt crafty and injurious. Theſe courſes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1782:29"/>too frequent &amp; palpable, may be diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when we finde moſt of the Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts uſing<note n="n" place="margin">Lucil.</note> all ſtudy and art warily to place their words, and cunningly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane themſelves, to cologue, and to counterfeit honeſt dealing. Thus<note n="o" place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. 45.</note> are they whited ſepulchers, outwardly beauteous, but inwardly full of rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. So that whilſt their ſlights are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned by a faining duty and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, they ſeeme honeſt men: but when the viſard is taken off, they appeare themſelves, ſuch indeed as cannot chuſe but bee held to be odious and deteſtable by all good men.<note place="margin">Seventhly, Banckrupts Injuſtice.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeventh fault of Banckrupts is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice: How can he chooſe but be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, that waſteth his eſtate and taketh Banckrupts courſes? For his chiefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire<note n="a" place="margin">Curt. B. 4.</note> and aime is to deceive, ſo that his heart muſt needs be far from all juſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. His minde is pitched upon his own gaine, ſo that<note n="b" place="margin">Ovid 2 Pont.</note> the venerable name of Juſtice ſits but like an harlot in the Porch, to call in Cuſtomers for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Some ulcers<note n="c" place="margin">Senec. of Tranq. c. 2.</note> there be, that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver better than when the hand doth chafe and rub them; ſuch an ulcer is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, which though it hurt a man,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1782:29"/>yet deſireth to be in action, and to have objects ſtill to worke on it. Let but<note n="d" place="margin">Plaut.</note> hope of gaine ſhew it ſelfe, the unjuſt man <hi>rem divinam deferet</hi> will omit his duty to God, rather than to his Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; for he that<note n="e" place="margin">Horat. ep. 1.</note> maketh haſte to bee rich, and plungeth himſelfe into the world, bids vertue adieu, ſleights<note n="f" place="margin">Plutarch</note> the repute of Juſtice, ſhameth at nothing, <hi>dum ob rem,</hi> will doe any thing, ſo it ſtand with his profit. For what will not mens hearts attempt, when an extreme thriftineſſe poſſeſſeth them?<note place="margin">Virgil. Aurt ſacra fames quià non cogit?</note> But they ſhall finde it better by much to leave this courſe of fraudulent dealing, in which death and deſtruction with baits tempting to injuſtice cloſely concealeth herſelfe, than to have continued therein to their future miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eightly, Banckrupts Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</note> The eight evill incident to Banckrupts is covetouſnes<note n="a" place="margin">Avarus aris avid alien. Agell.
<hi>10.5.</hi>
               </note> The dealings of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts ſhew them to be covetous and ravenous after other mens money, and to be like them,<note n="b" place="margin">Eraſm. in Adag.</note> who count nothing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, but gaine, to whom, as to their God, they conſecrate themſelves. By this they weigh out their godlineſſe, friendſhip, honeſty, fame, all things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and humane, and count all things
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1782:30"/>elſe but trifles; Their chiefe<note n="c" place="margin">Juvenal. ſat.
9.</note> prayers tend to this, that their wealth and ſtate may be advanced; this maketh abſtinence from other mens goods a ſtranger to them; this maketh them ready to catch, rake, and ſnatch what ever they can; yea<note n="d" place="margin">Baſil. homil. 7. againſt the Covetous.</note> how ever they be moderate in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, yet the further they proceed, the more potent they are, by the ruine of ſome caught in their ſnares, to catch and devoure others. Not unlike a River, which being ſmall and weake in the head, in the progreſſe receiveth ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, that with a violent ſtreame it carrieth all along with it: Banckrupts I ſay, if once through the impetuouſnes of a Covetous minde, they eſteeme gaine more than goodneſſe, wrong than equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, falſhood than truth,<note n="e" place="margin">Lamprid. in Comod.</note> every booty ſhall be conveyed into their boſome. Of this temper<note n="f" place="margin">Plutarch. in Ageſil.</note> were of old the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> who made the chiefe point of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and vertue to conſiſt in doing <hi>Sparta</hi> good; other juſtice they neither learned, nor knew; So being wholly poſſeſſed with this perſwaſion, they cared not whom they injured: Not unlike them are our Banckrupts, who to adorne their
<hi>Sparta,</hi> perſwade themſelves of ſingular
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1782:30"/>performance, if hiding their ſubtilties and perſidiouſneſſe, they can ſupplant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and rob them to enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Now if a man conclude with himſelf that each man deſireth<note n="g" place="margin">Terent. in Andr.</note> it ſhould rather goe well with himſelfe than with others, and proceed to an immenſe and unſatisfied deſire of having, and bound not his thirſt of getting within compaſſe of reaſon, at length all reſpect and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of Juſtice will be extinct, ſo that he will not onely ſay in his owne heart, but by his deeds proclame to the world,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Juvenal.</note> 
               <hi>habe as quaerat nemo, ſed oportet habere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inquire not whence a man hath his wealth, have it he muſt.</p>
            <p>O damnable ſpeech! beſeeming a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage! ſuch a Covetous heart ſtraying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of moderation and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, declareth openly the Speaker to be a Worldling and Mammoniſt, and not a Chriſtian; to be a ſtatue and Image having no more of the man in him than barely the name of a man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ninthly, Banckrupts lying.</note> The ninth fault of Banckrupts is lying. So that we reaſſume to Banckrupts the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1782:31"/>ſpeech which the Apoſtle borrowed: In Covetous<note n="a" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.3.</note> wiſe with fained words they play the Merchants. For furely they that ſtick not to lay covetous clutches upon other mens eſtates, they will not bluſh to cover truth over with the aſhes of lyes. The ſtudie<note n="b" place="margin">Circer. Agrac.</note> of gaine ſoone cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the ſtudy of fraud and lying; And if, as <hi>Salvian</hi> ſaith,<note n="c" place="margin">Book. 4.</note> the life of greedy and deceitfull tradeſmen be nothing els, but the hammering of deceit and forging out of lyes; Banckrupts may well be held to be the Chiefe,<note n="d" place="margin">Euripid. in Andro.</note> and Maſter-workmen of lying: for they uſe (thoſe called by <hi>Plautus</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Rudent.</note> magnificent lyes, and count lucre<note n="f" place="margin">Sophock in Athenaeus.</note> ſweet, though got by lying. This appeareth: Firſt, becauſe in their buying and ſelling they ſpeak<note n="g" place="margin">Jer. 9.8.</note>peaceably to their neighbours with their mouths, but in their hearts lay wait for them: So that there is no good agreement betweene their tongues and their hearts; I wiſh and pray God that they doe not in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie ſpeak lyes, having their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſeared with an hot iron as they 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. Then ſecondly, when the time of paying the principall cometh; theſe <hi>Doſoes</hi> great boaſters of their faire dealing, ſet the great<note n="h" place="margin">Juvenal. fat. 7.</note> bellowes on
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1782:31"/>worke to forge huge lyes. <hi>Strigelius</hi> hitts them right, ſaying, that they who willingly run in debt, unwillingly pay;<note place="margin">Ethick. B. 2.</note> and they that unwillingly pay, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell lyes: So that the firſt ſtep is being in debt, the ſecond is coyning of lyes; Thus lying and evill ſpeaking now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes aboundeth. Whence juſt ground have wee to ſay with the Prophet, let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man take heed of his friend, and let him not put confidence in a brother.<note place="margin">Jer. 9.4.</note> For every brother will ſupplant, and every friend will deale deceitfully; every one will deceive his friend, and will not ſpeake the truth; they have taught their tongues to ſpeake lyes and take great paines to doe wickedly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tenthly, Banckrupts. blemiſh the credit of their children and poſterity.</note> Furthermore, Banckrupts are tenthly very injurious to their children and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and by their fraudulent dealing lay an aſperſion and diſgrace on them, and brand them with Infamy; for when <hi rend="sup">b</hi> a foundation of a good name is not layed by the Parents, the ſtaine thereof falleth alſo on the Progenie.</p>
            <p>So that Firſt; the Children and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes be pointed at in publicke. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when they would ſpeake in the aſſembly, ſome one boldly interrupts<note n="a" place="margin">Cic. orat. for Sylla. Plutarch.</note>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1782:32"/>them and enjoyneth them ſilence; for<note n="c" place="margin">Laert. 2
1.</note> the vertuous and commendable life of the Parents is a Treaſure of freedome in ſpeech left to the Poſterity. Thirdly, when their children come into the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place and Exchange, where Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhew themſelves, preſently ſome will ſtep in, and with open mouths and bold faces give items to others to have no dealing with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or not to truſt them. Fourthly, if occaſion of marriage bee offered them with ſome honeſt Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens daughter, preſently ſome unlucky bird will ſing: take heed and be well adviſed; know you not, that his parents do <hi>animam debere</hi> owe more than they can pay? And<note n="d" place="margin">Terent. in Heaut.</note> thus this brute breaketh off the mariage. Thus Banckrupt parents are many wayes injurious to their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and poſterity.</p>
            <p>And here give mee leave to lay an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation againſt theſe unjuſt Parents: I know well<note n="e" place="margin">Cic. orat. for Cluent.</note> that Children ought not only to keep in ſilence injuries done them by their Parents, but alſo to take them patiently, and therefore quietly will I beare thoſe things which are to be borne, and in ſilence conceale them which are to be concealed. But this branding with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1782:32"/>Infamy and blaſting the credit of the Children, which proceedeth wholly from the Parents, who can keepe ſilent, who can be ſo patient as to bury it in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion? Is this fit? The old men<note n="f" place="margin">Aug. Medic.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the faults, the young Sons are put to the wrack; the Fathers ſwelled with pride, the Sons be brought low for it. They did devoure the ſweet gaine, theſe eat the bitter gall of diſgrace. The unjuſt offendeth, the juſt is puniſhed; the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty goeth away with the fault, the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſmarteth for it; The good man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, what the bad man deſerves: the Sonne-in-Law beareth the blame which the Father-in-Lawes ſin merited: what can be thought more grievous? Every<note n="g" place="margin">Cicer.</note> ingenuous man hath a deſire to partake and have a ſhare in true glory, which is the honourable fruit of true vertue; and further, there is no ingenuous and good nature but would willingly have a good name and fame derived upon him from his Parents and family: Why then doe you Banckrupts deprive your children and poſterity thereof? 'Tis too grievous<note n="h" place="margin">Cic. Brut.</note> That Parents ſins ſhould lye thus hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie on their children. By the bowels of tender compaſſion I intreat you, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1782:33"/>your ſelves, what you would anſwer, if your children ſhould thus ſpeake to you? Fathers, you begot<note n="i" place="margin">Cicer. in Catil.</note> us; next after God, you are Authors of our lives; you have given us education; but out alas, why are yee ſo bewitched with the love of gaine, that yee will be the ruine of our good names? Did your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents<note n="k" place="margin">Plaut. in Trim.</note> deliver ouer an unblemiſhed and unſtained fame to you, that you ſhould overthrow by your wickednes what they got by their vertue? that you ſhould be blemiſhes to the honor of your poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that you ſhould commit theſe things ſo bad, and ſo unbeſeeming your houſe and kindred?</p>
            <p>Think with your ſelves can any<note n="l" place="margin">Cicer. orat. to the Nobil.</note> thing be more neere and deere unto you than your owne children. Now how little doe you regard them, when by your ill courſes you brand them with infamy, and extinguiſh all the glory<note n="m" place="margin">Cicer. orat. for Sylla.</note> and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your ſtock, name and honor by your miſcariage? May not your poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie complaine of you, becauſe by you they are made heires of ſuch a calamitie, and for your ſakes are deſpiſed? ſhall not your children<note n="n" place="margin">Eccleſ. 41.10.</note> grieve at you their wicked fathers, becauſe by you they are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1782:33"/>expoſed to diſgrace and ſhame? will not God be offended with you and lay juſt judgement upon you? for he<note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> that hath not a care of his children &amp; houſhould, is worſe than an Infidell. Conſider, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things, I ſay, all yee, which bluſh not to pleaſe and ſolace your ſelves in the evill courſes of your moſt diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and unjuſt playing the Banckrupts.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the former evills,<note place="margin">Eleventhly, Banckrupts endanger their owne ſalvation.</note> the courſes of Banckrupts in the eleventh place draw them often into the loſſe of their owne Salvation. For, how can it otherwiſe be? when by hooke and crooke they unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inrich themſelves with other mens wealth, and rob others of their lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſo indanger the robbing of their owne ſouls of happines; <hi>Woe be to him,</hi> ſaith the Prophet;<note n="a" place="margin">Habac 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>which coveteth an evill covetouſneſſe to his owne houſe, and ſinneth againſt his own ſoule.</hi> Wonder not at this; for behold the<note n="b" place="margin">Ang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on the Pſa.</note> divell ſets before thine eyes, thy neighbours goods to intice thee to evill; theſe goods thou canſt not get without fraudulent dealing; They are the bait, fraud is the ſnare. O wretched man, why doſt thou ſo eye the bait, that thou ſeeſt not the ſnare? there is no way to get the goods, but by fraud
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1782:34"/>and ſubtilty, and if thou makeſt uſe of deceit and wiles, needs muſt thou bee taken, and if thou beeſt taken, what canſt thou expect but loſſe of thy ſoule?</p>
            <p>Hence it is that many catching at gold, captivate their ſoules, and for fruition of money adventure upon perdition of their owne ſalvation. O folly of men! who to advance their gaine run heedleſſe on their bane. What a madnes is it to get gold and loſe heaven? What<note n="c" place="margin">Aug. Serm. on Chriſts W.</note> profits a cheſt full of Gold, if the Soule be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of hope of Salvation? Wilt thou have good, and wilt not thou thy ſelfe bee good? bluſh, bluſh at the ſight of thy goods: ſith an houſe repleniſhed with goods calleth thee her Godleſſe maſter; <hi>What</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> 
               <hi>will it profit a man to gaine the whole world and loſe his owne Soule?</hi> or <hi>what can a man give in recompence for his ſoule?</hi> what can that which a rich man hath doe him good, if he have not God, who hath all things at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand?</p>
            <p>Theſe things ſhould be your dayly and ſerious meditation; but oh your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed and perverted reaſon! oh your unbridled deſires! oh your diſſolute counſells! How long will this your fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1782:34"/>delude you? whither will this your undounded licentiouſnes carry you? Are your minds ſo inflamed with folly, your deſires ſo infatuated with the love of money, that the feare of God and care of your Soules cannot make you more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, and with-draw you from your thirſting after Gold? Let the ſalvation of your ſoules move you, let it I ſay move you to conſider better of your courſes, for if the Soule be once loſt, you ſhall be for ever after moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>Thus far have we treated of the ſeverall kindes of ſins (the miſchievous joyes of perverted ſoules) which doe proceed from the fraudulent dealings of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts; we have painted out their folly in its due colours, but not ſo fully, as wee might have drawne it to the life: for there can be no ſuch depth of invention, no ſuch Copie of Elocution, no ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and incredible fluence of ſpeech, which can. I will not ſay fully expreſſe, but ſo much as number up the miſchiefs ariſing from the courſes of Banckrupts. Surely as Covetouſneſſe in the Antients eſteeme, comprehended in it all vices in a lump: So wee may judge, that the fraudulent courſes of Banckrupts have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1782:35"/>a Confluence in them of all evill: which any man will eaſily grant, if hee well and ſeriouſly weigh all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As for us, wee contented our ſelves in few words to lay open few of their evills in this briefe diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1782:35"/>
            <head>THE PRACTISE OF THE BANCKRVPTS OF OUR TIMES.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>The third Part,</hi> Which declareth the puniſhments decreed to be inflicted upon them.</head>
            <head type="sub">Great puniſhments have been decreed for Banckrupts.</head>
            <p>WHat then ſhall Banckrupts run on in their ſins unpuniſhed? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid: ſhall
<hi>bonorum extortor</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Terent. Senec. 3. of Benefi.</note> 
               <hi>legum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortor,</hi> a cheater of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a wreſter of lawes eſcape? Can courſes ſo hatefull paſſe unpuniſhed? The Heathen Oracle
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1782:36"/>ſaid; Never did any<note n="c" place="margin">Herodot.</note> man guilty of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt dealing eſcape the whip of revenge. Tis<note n="d" place="margin">Menand</note> as it were fatall and unavoidable, that the unjuſt and injurious deſignes of evill men ſhould be required with their deſerved doome. Even the wiſeſt ſort of Heathens held<note n="e" place="margin">Saluſt.</note> it for a truth that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the good nor the evill deeds of men ſhould paſſe unregarded: but that a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent requitall ſhould attend both good and bad, according to the nature of their deeds. And herein rightly have humane lawes imitated the true patterne of Gods Juſtice: for our Anceſtors<note n="f" place="margin">Tacitus Ann.</note> have ordained that where Crimes went before, due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſhould follow after. Let us then briefly collect the ſeverall lawes of our forefathers enacted againſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and in order ſet downe what hath been decreed. Firſt, by the lawes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Secondly, by the Ceſarean lawes. Thirdly, by ſeverall Kings lawes. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the Common law. Fifthly, by Gods Law. So ſhall we meet with thoſe fraudulent perſons in many of their evill and enormous dealings. And ſurely needs muſt theſe Banckrupts be a moſt wicked and bad kinde of men,<note place="margin">Benven.</note> had wee no other Argument to prove it, than ſo many ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1782:36"/>and lawes in ſeverall parts of the world which have been ordein'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; reforme their naughtines. Let us now in particular ſet downe the lawes and ordinances of the Antients, in their own words and tenor.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The lawes of Nations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</note> The Lawes of Nations, by which in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Commonwealths the ſtates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are upheld, have an aime and reſpect to this; That humane ſocietie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction may be kept in ſafetie: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any man treſpaſſe againſt this, they inflict on him death, or baniſhment, or impriſoning, or amercement. Now heare their different lawes againſt banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</p>
            <p>The Romans decreed that the debter owing very much to his creditors,<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex. B. 6.10</note> ſhould ſatisfie his debts by deviding his ſubſtance amongſt them; and being deprived of all his goods, ſhould be put into priſon and Chaines, and afterwards that his joynts ſhould be devided, at the pleaſure of the Creditors amongſt them.</p>
            <p>The Egyptians ordeined that ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhould bee made by the debtors goods and eſtate, but no puniſhment to to be inflicted on the body;<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ibidem.</note> for they held mens goods lyable to ſatisfie for debts of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1782:37"/>money, and not their bodies; yet they uſed to pawne the embalmed bodies of the dead for money, and held it for an extreme diſgrace, if the debtors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them not at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Boetians</hi> he that could not pay his debts,<note place="margin">Srobeus Serm.
42.</note> was thus diſgraced by the basket. He was to be brought and ſet in the open market with a basket on his head. He that had thus ſat, was ever after held infamous. This puniſhment
<hi>Mne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarchas</hi> the father of <hi>Euripides</hi> the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedian</hi> ſuffered.</p>
            <p>Among the Indians,<note place="margin">Alex. of Alex. ibidem.</note> hee that paid not his debts, if hee was called in queſtion and ſued by his Creditors, a day was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them, and then if he ſatisfied not, firſt his hand was cut off, and his eye put out, and then he was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Piſidians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stoheus Serm. 42.</note> any one defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creditors of what was committed to any man in truſt, was very ſeverely puniſhed, for he that defrauded, was put to a moſt cruell death.</p>
            <p>Amongſgt the <hi>Tyrrhenians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heraclid. in polit.</note> if any man paid not the money which he borrowed, by publike appointment Boyes followed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1782:37"/>him which an emptie purſe for his utter diſgrace.</p>
            <p>The Judgement upon Banckrupts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Smyrneans</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caelius Antiq. lect. 70.20</note> was, that they which according to Covenant did not give due content to their Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, were for ever excluded, and forbid to come into the market.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Muſcovits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guagin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Muſcov c.
4.</note> debtors that have not wherewithall to ſatisfy their Creditors, are according to their lawes brought into a publick place ordeined for that end, and there grievouſly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mercy beaten with whips and wands on the leggs and feet, till they make full payment to their Creditors, whenceſoever they can get it: if they cannot get wherewithall to ſatisfy, then being often whipt, they are compelled to become ſervants to the Creditors, thereby to ſatisfie them according to the valew of the debt.</p>
            <p>Among the Iurkes when any ones fraudulent dealing is detected,<note place="margin">Aerod. B.
1</note> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor adjudges him to death.</p>
            <p>Among the Florentines if any bee Banckrupt, and be convicted ſo to be, there is appointed him a certaine day of payment,<note place="margin">Brut. B. 1. hiſt, Florent.</note> as ſeemes fit in the Magiſtrates
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1782:38"/>diſcretion, at which day if the debtor pay not, his name is regiſtred among the fraudulent Banckrupts, and he is depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his freedome and diſabled to give his voyce as a Citizen: He on whom this puniſhment is inflicted, is ſaid to bee brought to be looking glaſſe, becauſe in that Catalogue as in a glaſſe, you may ſee the worth and eſtate of ſuch men.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Roan</hi> the Banckrupts and men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent, are made to weare a greene hat, that by this badge they may be knowne from all other men, and that no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares may enter into Covenant and bargaine with them which uſed to faile and be inſolvent.</p>
            <p>Hence it appeareth how contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly divers Nations and people have thought of debtors branded with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny of falſe dealing or notorius Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts courſes.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> lawes againſt Banckrupts have been many.<note place="margin">2 The Caeſarean lawes againſt Banckrupts.</note> In the dayes of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth were made many conſtitutions and many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts promulgated, by which it was thought good to prevent divers frauds ptactiſed in buying and ſelling and in ſubtle ſupplanting men of their eſtates,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1782:38"/>as alſo grievous and dire puniſhments aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to Banckrupts, according to their demerits. This well beſeemed the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarean Authority; for he knoweth how to rule well, who hath a ſpeciall regard that a Corporation be not infected with evill men, and that Merchants &amp; Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be free from perfidious and falſe dealing. For a Cities<note n="a" place="margin">Epicter.</note> ſafegard depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not upon the ſtrength of the walls, but the vertue and juſt dealing of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens; Nor is<note n="b" place="margin">As ſaid An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus.</note> there any ſurer bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke to defend a kingdome, than the mutuall love and faire dealing and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt demeanor of the ſubjects. The Poet ſaid well, that a Citie is ſtrongly<note n="c" place="margin">Plaut. in Perſa.</note> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, if the Citizens be vertuous. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if, Firſt, falſe dealing. Secondly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienating the common treaſure. Thirdly, Covetouſneſſe. Fourthly, Envie. Fifthly, Ambition. Sixthly, Calumniation. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venthly, Perjury. Eigthly, Slothfulnes in mens vocations. Ninthly, Oppreſſion. Tenthly, Murther (which falleth heavie upon the committer) if I ſay theſe vices be not baniſhed the Citie, an hundred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold wall is too little to defend it. Now ſuppoſe the ſtate of a Kingdome be ſuch, that ſome of theſe vices, at leaſt one of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1782:39"/>them, namely fraudulent dealing abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly raigne in peoples mindes: The queſtion is what ſhall the chiefe Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate doe? Shall he wink at it, or inflict ſevere puniſhment thereon? Too much mildneſſe and too much ſeveritie are both culpable, the one lets the reines of government hang too looſe, th'other holds them in too ſtreight; reaſon and moderation is ſo to be uſed in puniſhing, that a Magiſtrate obſerve a due temper of Juſtice, and juſtly puniſh unjuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauders of other men:<note place="margin">Hieronym. to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ius.</note> for if a Judge puniſh an offence, as he is Gods Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, it is not cruelty, but pietie, and <hi>Bleſſed is hee who doth juſtice at all times.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 106.3.</note> Let no man then wonder at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Charles the Fifths</hi> Conſtitution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Banckrupts, promulgated after this manner.</p>
            <p>This Conſtitution of <hi>Charles the Fifth</hi> againſt Banckrupts, was enacted and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, <hi>Octob.</hi> 7. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1531.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="edict">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>Charles by the Grace of God, Roman Emperor, &amp;c.</signed>
                        <salute>Againſt inſolvent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive perſons or Banckrupts.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>We for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ordeined, and further ordeine, That all Merchants and Chapman or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or others that deale in buying and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1782:39"/>ſelling, who doe fraudulently and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully beguile other Merchants or perſons whatſoever of their moneyes, wares, or debts, ſhall be counted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted in the ſame ranck and condition with arrant theeves. And by this ſtatute wee have and doe declare them ſo to bee.</p>
                     <p>In like manner we declare our ſaid minde to bee concerning all ſuch as tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, enterteine, or by ſilence countenance them, as alſo all them that are privie to the ſaid Banckrupts frauds, and imbezel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of other mens goods, and know whither they bee fled, and where they hide themſelves; unleſſe they manifeſt theſe things unto the Judge or chiefe Magiſtrate of the place. Furthermore we count them in the ſame rank with theeves, who craftily agitate the buſines of banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, who be the Receivers or Retaylers of their wares, whether under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and name of partners or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as alſo all them that pretend and faine themſelves to be creditors of banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, by whoſe meanes the fraud and perfidiouſneſſe of the Banckrupts may be concealed or boulſterd out.</p>
                     <p>All the aforeſaid we have and doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1782:40"/>of all the immunities, liberties, and priviledges of all Cities, and Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Townes, and places to whom freedome in any kinde hath been in any manner granted.</p>
                     <p>And we bid and command that Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts and their Partners, Helpers and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, and all above named, found and adjudged to be ſo, as alſo all perſons that fly for debt into any Citie, Towne, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or any priviledged place, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, none excepted, be fetched and taken thence, and that their goods and eſtates, if they brought any thither, bee taken thence: Notwithſtanding we will that the priviledges and liberties of the ſaid Cities, Townes, and places whatſoever, enjoying any freedome, abide and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue unto them, in all other cauſes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. And alſo, We ordeine, that the Banckrupts and their Aſſiſtants before ſpecified, being proved and adjudged ſo to be, ſhall be puniſhed as Theeves and violaters of the publick good, and that without Connivence or delay, for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all others.</p>
                     <p>And further that the goods and eſtate of the ſaid Banckrupts and their Agents and helpers be taken from them, and be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1782:40"/>depoſited and kept in ſome place conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, for the benefit and right of the Creditors, as ſhall in Juſtice be thought meet.</p>
                     <p>Further, that the Wives of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or Traders, who prove inſolvent, and the goods in which their Wives, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Husbands preſence or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, have dealt by buying or ſelling in open Market, be lyable to anſwer for, and ſatisfie the Husbands debts, in which he ingaged himſelfe during the time of their marriage.</p>
                     <p>Wee will alſo and Command that all Merchants and Chap-men or women, who fraudulently to deceive their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, flye out of our dominions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide elſewhere, within forty dayes after the publication of this edict, doe returne into the place of their uſuall dwelling in our Territories, and that within forty dayes more they make ſatisfaction to their Creditors, which thing unleſſe they doe within the forty latter dayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: We ordeine that the Banckrupts themſelves, as alſo all their aſſiſtants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, be for ever baniſhed out of our Territories and dominions, never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into them againe.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:1782:41"/>
                     <p>Furthermore, wee Command that all Contracts fainedly, fallaciouſly, and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently made, be fruſtrate and of no force and validity. And that all the Creditors of Banckrupts, and their Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and of other fugitives for debt, joyne together in the felling of the Banckrupts goods, and whatſoever can be found, for the diſcharge of the Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts debts, and that a regard be had to the proportion and valew of each Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors debt without any partiality to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie any particular man.</p>
                     <p>Neither ſhall any Creditor benefit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by preventing others in arreſting the goods of any decayed perſon, though it be done in any priviledge place what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: Nor ſhall the Cuſtomes, rights, or lawes of any place whatſoever, made to the contrary, hinder what herein we Command: for our pleaſure is, That in the foreſaid caſes they be of no force, and that if the cauſe ſo require, by this our conſtitution they be of no validity.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Kings lawes againſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</note> 3 Divers worthy provident and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Kings have enacted ſtrict lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Banckrupts. <hi>Plato</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Plat. in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cib.</note> ſaid well, that the Providence of a Governor conſiſteth in conſulting well for his owne and his peoples welfare.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:1782:41"/>
            <p>This thing the French Kings, truly carefull of their peoples good, duely weighing, moſt providently enacted good lawes for the due puniſhing of Banckrupts; for being informed that this crime grew too too common by its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity (which is<note n="b" place="margin">Cicer. Orat.</note> a great bait to draw on offences) and that trading and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce was quite taken away by the breach of Compacts and fidelity; which falſe dealing would prove the weakning of Kingly State, they therefore made ſpeciall uſe of their princely power in purging out all great enormities of Banckrupts: This may appeare in their ſeverall decrees againſt them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of that name King of France decreed <hi>Anno</hi> 1536 That Banckrupts, and their partners, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutors ſhould be ſeverely dealt with, and diligent inquirie made, witneſſes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extraordinary remedies uſed, and the fault apparantly found, the perſons guilty ſhould have ſome corporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment inflicted on them, according to their deſert, either by putting them into the pillorie, or ſome other way, as ſhould ſeeme good to the Judge. In which decree what may ſeeme ſevere?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1782:42"/>ſeeing<note n="c" place="margin">Cic. Offic. 2.</note> that for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſeveritie is to be uſed, without which no ſtate can bee well ordered. Better is it by<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. 9.</note> ſeverity to expreſſe love to the Commonwealth, than by lenity to ruinate it. Wee cut off a finger, that the gangrene may not proceed to the Arme: So offendors are juſtly puniſhed, that their ſin proceed not further to the detriment of the whole bodie politike.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Charles the niuth</hi> King of France in an aſſembly of the Peeres and States, at Orleance, did conſtitute that fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Banckrupts ſhould be extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed, and afterward put to death. Who can finde fault with this? The publicke good ſo required; for hee<note n="d" place="margin">Plut.</note> wrongeth good men, who conniveth at the bad: And the place of a King and his office is to puniſh offenders<note n="e" place="margin">Hieronym. on Jerem.</note> and relieve the innocent: Hee is the diſpencer<note n="f" place="margin">Ariſt. polit.</note> of Juſtice, and will not ſuffer the rich to be invaded by the poore, nor the poore contumeliouſly uſed by the wealthy.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Henry the third</hi> renewed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed this edict againſt againſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts at Bloys, <hi>Anno</hi> 1579. And let not any man hence tax him of ſeverity: for hee that ſits at the ſterne in the tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1782:42"/>ſea of Civill affaires, ought ever to have his eyes bent and intent to advance the Common good of all;<note place="margin">Cic. Offic. 1.</note> And men in authoritie are to provide for, as the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo the benefit of the people who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to their place, and not to minde onely their owne profit and ſafety who are called thereunto: And herein eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially differeth, ſaith <hi>Aristotle,</hi> a King from a Tyrant, the one ſtudieth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth his owne benefit, the other the Subjects welfare.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Henry the Fourth</hi> Succeſſor to the former, as in Kingly authority, to in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent adminiſtration of Juſtice, did by his Royall edict ſeverely meet with the Crafty arts &amp; audacious tricks in Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts courſes. Read his conſtitution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Banckrupts and failing tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enacted in the ſupreme Court, June 4. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1609. Thus far of the French Kings edicts againſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lawes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land made concerning Banckrupts.</note> Nor have the Princes of England been backward in this kind, but have ſeriouſly conſidered the miſchiefs which were incident to Commerce and humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie and to the well ordering of the Commonwealth, and which have been
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1782:43"/>pulled upon us by the ſubtle and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable &amp; ungodly dealings of Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and thereupon our ſaid Kings have with great care and circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on provided good and wholſome lawes to prevent or puniſh Banckrupts cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Anno</hi> 34.
<hi>Hen.</hi> 8. A ſtatute was was enacted for remedying the harmes and evils befalling this land by Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno</hi> 13. of <hi>Fliz. cap.</hi> 7. more fully was declared what Merchants or Tradeſmen, &amp;c. departing this Realme, or keeping their houſes, or willingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arreſted, &amp;c. to defraud their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, &amp;c. ſhall be counted Banckrupts. And further is enacted, how Commiſſion ſhall be granted, by which the body and goods whatſoever of the ſaid Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts may be ſeized upon, and how by the Commiſſioners a courſe ſhal be taken for ſatisfying of the Banckrupts debts: As alſo how the Comiſſioners ſhall have authority to finde out and diſpoſe of the Banckrupts goods, lands, &amp;c. in the hands of any other perſon whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and how they ſhall by oath of any perſon ſuſpected to have the goods of the Banckrupts, endeavour to finde out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1782:43"/>the truth: Beſides in this ſtatute penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are impoſed on the Banckrupts who hide or convey themſelves from their u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall places of aboad, and on ſuch as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly and willingly help to hide or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey any perſon proclaymed Banckrupt and going about to conceale himſelfe. See more in the ſaid Act.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno.</hi> 1. <hi>Iacobic.</hi> 15. Becauſe banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts fraud and deceit increaſed, (as it is there ſaid) to the hindrance of traffick &amp; to the generall hurt of the Realme, it is further explained, who are to be reputed Banckrupts, and how the power of the Commiſſioners ſhould be further inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Alſo it is enacted, That if Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts by conveying their lands, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, leaſes, goods, Chattells, &amp;c. to their Children, or any other perſon; or perſons, ſeeke and endeavour to defraud their Creditors: That then the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall have power to bargaine, ſell, grant, demiſe, convey, and diſpoſe of the ſame, as if the Banckrupts had been actually poſſeſſed thereof, or as if the debts were in his owne name. And that the acts of the Commiſſioners in this kinde ſhall be good in law againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, who ſhall queſtion the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:1782:44"/>
            <p>See theſe things in that act more largely ſet downe.</p>
            <p>It is there alſo further enacted that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the practiſes of Banckrupts were become ſecret, ſubtill, and hardly to be found out, in what caſes any one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing him or herſelf from their uſuall aboad, ſhall be proclaymed Banckrupt, and how the ſaid Banckrupt not appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the ſaid Commiſſioners, is to be apprehended, whereever hee or ſhee may be found, in places priviledged or not, and are to be examined by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners about their own lands, goods, debts, books of accounts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is alſo enacted that if the offendor refuſe to anſwer to the Interrogatories propounded, that then the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall have power to commit him or her to cloſe priſon, till they conforme themſelves. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo enacted, that if the partie examined commit wilfull or corrupt perjury to the endamagement of the Creditors, ten pounds or more, hee or ſhe ſhall bee indicted, &amp;c. And being convicted ſhall bee ſet on the pillory, and have one care nayled thereto and cut off. As alſo ſuch as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1782:44"/>have Banckrupts goods or bee indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, ſhall bee examined by the Commiſſioners, and how if in caſe they refuſe to appeare, or if they appeare and refuſe to anſwer to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, the Commiſſioners ſhall have power to cauſe them to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted and made to appeare, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward may impriſon them till they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves to the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and anſwer to the ſaid Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: And if any of the ſaid parties ſhall wilfully and corruptly commit any manner of wilfull perjurie by his depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition before the Commiſſioners, that then it ſhall be lawfull to indict the ſaid perſons, and upon their conviction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne them ſuch forfeiture, and lay upon them ſuch paines and puniſhments, as was limited <hi>Anno quinto Eliz.</hi> by the Statute of perjurie. Further alſo it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided concerning the Commiſſioners, how they ſhall proceed and maintaine their proceedings for the good of the Creditors, and the Banckrupt, and for their owne diſcharge of the truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. And how they ſhall proceed to execution of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though the Banckrupt die. See
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1782:45"/>theſe things more fully declared in the Statute.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Anno</hi> 21. <hi>Iac.</hi> In regard that Banckrupts much increaſed in number, and their fraudes were many in deluding the former ſtatutes, to the hinderance of traffick and Commerce, and the great decay and overthrow and undoing of Clothiers, &amp;c. So that the Banckrupts evill-dealings tended (as juſtly there is affirmed) to the generall hurt of this Realme: It is there enacted that all lawes made againſt Banckrupts, ſhall bee beneficially conſtrued for the good of the Creditors. There alſo is more expreſly ſhewed who are to be accompted banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, what the authority of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners is, what ſhall be the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lawes in force againſt Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts. 'Tis further enacted that the wives of Banckrupts ſhall be examined in the ſame manner, as was before ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the husbands. As alſo in what caſe the Banckrupt and his wife ſhall be ſet on the pillory, &amp;c. Alſo it is there provided how the Banckrupts goods &amp; eſtate ſhall be devided to the Creditors. Alſo how Banckrupts making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves accomptants to the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1782:45"/>ſhall not hinder the proceedings of the Commiſſioners to right the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Theſe things and many more are conteined and more fully and largely ſet down in the foreſaid ſtatutes concerning Banckrupts, for the utter rooting out of all Banckrupts courſes, and the bridling and reforming of ſo great a miſchiefe to the Common good. Leaving therefore theſe things to the Readers peruſall in the book of the Statutes at large, we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to cite any more out of them: And having here inſerted what wee thought moſt expedient for our owne Nation to take notice of; Let us proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. The Canon Laws againſt Banckrupts.</note> Fourthly, nor have the Common laws paſſed over the perfidious courſes of Banckrupts and Covenant-breakers, but puniſhed them by degrees according to their deſerts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They lay a blemiſh and ſtaine upon their credit and reputation, who faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pay not their debts: for in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, it is ſaid, he<note n="a" place="margin">8. Rule of the Canon Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that is once a falſe dealer, is ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſo to be. Thus the honour &amp; name of a good man is taken from a Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt: who ſheweth himſelfe by his frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent courſe and dealing, and by palliat
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1782:46"/>and pretended honeſty, to be a knave, and utterly unworthy to be truſted, or to have Covenant kept with him.<note place="margin">Book 5. Rul. 75. of the Can. Law.</note> For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly doth hee require others to obſerve fidelity towards him, who breaks it at pleaſure towards them; Beſides in the ancient ſtatutes of the Church, it was<note n="c" place="margin">Canon 12.</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned, that he which invadeth another mans goods, ſhould not eſcape unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſhould make reſtitution of all with advantage.</p>
            <p>The ſecond decree of puniſhment was confirmed by a Statute of <hi>Iohn the Fourth</hi> Pope of that name; He that invadeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens goods let him reſtore them foure-fold. Yea,
<hi>Euſebius</hi> the Pope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, that<note n="e" place="margin">Ibid.</note> reſtitution ten-fold ſhould be made.</p>
            <p>The third puniſhment of ſuch as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly poſſeſſe themſelves of other mens goods, is, that they ſhould hope for no remiſſion of their ſins, untill they had made reſtitution; for<note n="f" place="margin">Bonifac. 8. Rul 4. in the Can. Law.</note> 
               <hi>Peccatum non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, niſi reſtituatur ablatum.</hi> And that there can be no repentance, unleſſe the goods ill gotten bee reſtored, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by this ſpeech of
<hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Macedonians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 5.</note> There is no performance of Repentance, if the goods
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1782:46"/>of other men bee not reſtored.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To bring Banckrupts to a true ſence of their ſinnes, and to fit them for Gods gratious work upon them, and the obteyning of pardon of their offences, by the edict of the Lateran Councell was decreed, that they ought<note n="h" place="margin">Lateran. Conc. under Fabian.</note> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, who poſſeſſe themſelves of mens goods, unleſſe they reſtore them to their owners, their heires or others, to whom by law the wronged perſons goods deſcended, becauſe they rob and deprive them of their eſtates, whom ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of Faith they ought to relieve.</p>
            <p>See here how antiently decrees were made to withdraw men from fraudulent dealings, ſuch as are the ſubtilties of Banckrupts, and to lay Condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them. As men cut of thoſe parts of their bodies, which want blood &amp; ſpirit, and would harme other joynts: So evils are to bee taken away from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, and to be rooted out by good lawes, leſt they prove pernitious and hurtfull to the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or the parts and members of the ſame; Of which kinde, we accompt the Courſes of Banckrupts in getting into
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1782:47"/>their clutches other mens goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and defrauding them thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Divine Laws againſt Banckrupts. Curt. 7.</note> Some may think the Canon Law milde, becauſe it inflicteth no ſevere puniſhment on fraudulent and crafty Banckrupts. Come wee then Fifthly, to ſpeak of divine vengeance which no man can eſcape, who layeth Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and falſe fingers on other mens goods. The Heathen Poet could ſay, <hi>They who blinded with</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yp.</note> 
               <hi>folly, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with madneſſe, out of opinion and hope of gaine, neglect Iuſtice, ſhall ſurely ſmart for it:</hi> God whom they ſee not, will come upon them with a ſilent foot, and though long after, will catch the wretched man. Thus ſaith the Poet; As if he had learned from <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. That he is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God whoſoever doth what God forbids and deales unjuſtly.</p>
            <p>Now God puniſheth ſuch falfe dealers ſeverally.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>With externall puniſhments in this life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Internall puniſhments in this life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>With grievous puniſhments after this life.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Banckrupts perhaps promiſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much happineſſe by lurching o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their goods; but behold how
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1782:47"/>they (ſuch namely as bee wicked men among them) beguile themſelves, not minding how great damage ſo ſmall gaine bringeth unto them.</p>
            <p>Heare yee this,<note n="c" place="margin">Amos 8 4.</note> yee that devoure the poore, and thruſt the needy out of the earth! Alas deceived ſouls, of all miſerable men the moſt miſerable, I appeale to your ſelves, you Banckrupts, who get into your hands great ſums of money lent you, and with ſet purpoſe and intent run your Countries, &amp; faine falſe courſes by which you loſt them, that having put your Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors to troubles ſuits, and expence, and thereby wearied them, you may force them having been thus vexed, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with you upon unreaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. I pray you ſay what you ſhall gaine in the end, when for that fading pelfe, which you have ſo greedily and falſly hunted after, and got by hook and crook, you ſhall at laſt reap a ſad and fearefull harveſt. O ſad and lamentable harveſt, of externall and internall paines in this life, and of endleſſe paines after this life: Of theſe I will now ſpeake in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God hath appointed externall divine puniſhment to be laid on Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:1782:48"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Externall divine puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on Banckrupts.</note> Certaine it is that God the Law-giver hath aſſigned juſt puniſhment to them that unjuſtly get other mens goods into their hands. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.4. he maketh this law; that he which taketh away ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans goods, ſhall make reſtitution five fold, or double, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the theft. And that if he have not wherewith to give ſatisfaction, that he be ſold, for making good the theft: Nor doth it much skill by what means hee doth get another mans goods, and taketh them as his owne poſſeſſion: Seing God will not have this rule of Juſtice, (that each man ſhould enjoy his owne eſtate and meanes) by any wicked courſe to be violated, without due puniſhment; yea that<note n="a" place="margin">Jod. Nahum Domin. 22. Trin.</note> by no meanes, equity may be left unvindicated, God hath concluded that not the debtors only, but their wives and children ſhould be taken and become ſervants to the Creditors.</p>
            <p>This ſhall be made evident by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and examples: As it was lawfull among the Hebrewes<note n="b" place="margin">Ex. 21.7. Lev. 25.39. Deut. 15.12.</note> for a man to fell himſelfe and his Children alſo, when hee was impoveriſhed: So it is credible that there was ſome Magiſtrate, who at the ſuit of the Creditors, when the debtors
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1782:48"/>were inſolvent, did require them to ſell themſelves, and their children, that by this courſe the debt might be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>This may manifeſtly enough be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the parable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. of the King who had bid that his debtor and his ſonnes might be ſold, that pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be made.</p>
            <p>With this agreeth 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. Where a Widow complayneth to <hi>Eliſha</hi> that her Creditor did preſſe her earneſtly, that he would take her two Sons from her to be his ſervants.</p>
            <p>What condition is more grievous than ſervitude? If our deere children and wives ſhould be taken from us, and put to perpetuall ſervitude, what lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what ſighes would theſe put us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? Now it is evident by theſe places of Scripture, that debtors, who were not able to pay, were in thoſe times ſold, that fidelity might be obſerved, and every man might have what in truth was due unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Internall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Secondly, God hath appointed inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall puniſhments to light upon Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts; even ſuch paines as will not onely outwardly afflict the body, but inwardly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1782:49"/>alſo trouble the minde; ſuch as are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, feare, ſting of Conſcience: for Conſcience<note n="a" place="margin">Cic. or at. for Cluent.</note> is implanted in us by the immortall God, ſo that it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. And truly God hath for our great good given it into us, that it might be<note n="b" place="margin">Origen.</note> the Corrector of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the tutor of our reaſon, that it might be a bridle to us before we ſinne, becauſe<note n="c" place="margin">Senec epiſt.</note> it hath in it a deteſtation of that thing which nature condemneth; and a ſcourge after ſinne, becauſe when ſin is committed, it underſtandeth the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſnes of it.</p>
            <p>This we ſee to be true by experience in unjuſt men, which though they be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed and defended which the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and aſſiſtance of great men, yet when their conſciences are troubled, their mindes are inwardly gnawed with wondrous torments, which never give them a breathing ſpace, never ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſt. So that they are not unlike to
<hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Horac.</note> who is ſaid to be chained upon the hill <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> and to have his liver torne continually by a devouring Vulture. In this manner fareth it with Banckrupts, who rob others of their money. So that if not in the very act, yet ſoone after it,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1782:49"/>they feele grievous ſtings and whips, which for their frauds and wicked ſhifts like tormentors doe gore and laſh them.</p>
            <p>For no<note n="e" place="margin">Sen. epiſt.</note> man can long joy in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of his fraudulent Courſes: fall out it will ſooner or later that evill men ſhall find how they have purchaſed a prey little worth, with great loſſe and heavy diſcommodity. But thou wilt ſay, thy laugh, and rejoyce. I confeſſe it, but their joy at their bankets is not a true and right joy: Surely tis no other than joy of ſuch as lying in priſon adjudged to death, ſometimes play at cards and dice, and think to beguile their griefe, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; for the terror of the puniſhment ſhortly to be inflicted is ſo deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in their minds, that it cannot bee removed. The repreſentation of pale death, ſtill attendeth in their ſight; ſo the puniſhment due to the wicked dealings of unjuſt Banck rupts &amp; inſolvent tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſticketh faſt in their mindes and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth them not to reſt. The conſcience privy to their wicked fraudulent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious dealing, doth diſquiet and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify them with reſtleſſe and diſtracting thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:1782:50"/>
            <p>Theſe are the continuall<note n="g" place="margin">Cic.</note> and home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred furies, which day and night hale wicked men to puniſhment, which trouble the fraudulent and impure heart, that it can be quieted neither ſleeping nor waking. O moſt wretched men, whoſe<note n="h" place="margin">Juvenal.</note> minds a guiltie conſcience laſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with ſtripes, which others heare not!</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Divine pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Banckrupts after this life.</note> 3. There are grievous puniſhments after this life to be by Gods Juſtice layd upon Banckrupts. Now goe too, you Banckrupts, howle and lament for the miſeries, which ſhall come upon you; you have done<note n="a" place="margin">Gualt. in Hab.</note> much evill unto other men, but yet yee have robbed them of nought but tranſitory and momentary riches; whoſe loſſe may bee repaired ſundry wayes; but in this Circumven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others, you have defrauded your ſelves of endleſſe happineſſe, and plunged your ſelves into hell: For, God<note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 5.7.</note> abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minateth the deceitfull man, and will deſtroy all workers of iniquity: and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth that the wicked ſhall not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the Kingdome of Heaven. But what is that I heare? you ſay, who<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 23.24.</note> ſeeth us? darkneſſe encompaſſeth us, the walls hide us, and no man ſeeth us, what ſhould
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1782:50"/>we feare? God on high remembreth not our ſins. Be not deceived; certaine it is, that we muſt all appeare before<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 10. 2 Cor. 5.</note> the Judgment Seat of Chriſt: that every one may receive according to that which he hath done in his body, whether good or evill: your inward and your outward actions, all your ſins ſhall be ballanced; behold<note n="e" place="margin">Jud. 11 &amp; 14</note> the Lord commeth with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Angels to bring all men to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to judge all wicked men for all their impious works; your words, whether they be idle or deceitfull, muſt bee accounted for, and your thoughts whatſoever muſt come to Judgment, and then your conſcience ſhall beare witneſſe, and your thoughts accuſe or excuſe one another in that day, in which God ſhall judge by Jeſus Chriſt all the ſecrets of men according to the Goſpell. Then fourthly in a word, account ſhall be taken of you for all the extent of your whole lives, in what manner you have ſpent it. Woe to you poore ſouls. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will yee goe? if yee be found in your ſins, where will bee your refuge?</p>
            <p>And fifthly, whereas in times paſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders fled to Temples and Altars, and debtors might not be taken thence by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1782:51"/>their Creditors; and at this day there be priviledged places, which as Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, keep Banckrupts and inſolvent men from moleſtation; in the laſt day the frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent cannot eſcape, there will be no Sanctuary to protect them.</p>
            <p>And ſixthly, there will be no eſcape, no ſtarting-hole, no ſhifting for male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors: there can be no colour to cloake their lies and cheating, no pretence ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to boulſter out their frauds &amp; guile. Such as had nothing truly their owne, but a tongue to lie and forſware, and fraudulent cunning tricks and wicked devices to rend and teare in peeces other mens eſtates, and leave them with bare and naked corps, ſhall truly appeare themſelves and ſhew what they are.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, let them conſider that<note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet 4.5.</note> God the Judge of quicke and dead, is moſt juſt; that he will put on righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a breſt plate, and true judgment inſteed of an helmet, and ſo adjudge all men; that<note n="g" place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, ſhall be bewen downe and caſt into the fire. And if<note n="h" place="margin">Fulgent. in Matt.</note> barrenneſſe and want of doing good be caſt into hell fire, what will falſe dealers and robbers of other eſtates deſerve? If hee bee<note n="i" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dei.</note> caſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1782:51"/>into the fire, who hath not been libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in giving his owne goods; into what ſhall he be throwne, that hath taken away other mens goods? if hee burne with the divell that clothed not the naked; where ſhall he burne, that tooke away his clothing? They<note n="k" place="margin">Hugo B. 2. of the Soule.</note> are juſtly puniſhed who abuſe their owne lawfull goods: So Satan loſt Heaven and <hi>Adam</hi> Paradiſe; but more juſtly ſhall they be plagued, who unjuſtly rob others of their eſtates.</p>
            <p>Thus have you heard, what will be the puniſhments of Backrupts. In due time take heed, and avoid unjuſt dealing, and conceive that what is here ſpoken, is as a bitter pill, not to pleaſe, but to profit you; diſtaſtfull to your eares, but ſerving for the Cure of your hearts, that yee may be drawne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by the feare of danger and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments hanging over your heads, and ſo to<note n="l" place="margin">Luk 21.36.</note> be counted worthy to eſcape miſeries to come, and to ſtand before the Son of man.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:1782:52"/>
            <head>THE PRACTISE OF THE BANCKRVPTS OF THESE TIMES.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>The fourth Part,</hi> Concerning the remedy of their practiſes.</head>
            <p>TIs now full time to come to the remedies of Banckrupts practiſes: For we have layd open their wounds, not out of a deſire to hurt them, or ſhame them: but to better them, and cure their maladies. Now as Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans having found the cauſes of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,<note place="margin">Tuſcul. qu. 3.</note> thinke the cure alſo found: So wee having found the cauſes of this
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1782:52"/>miſchiefe and ſickneſſe, will atempt to diſcover the remedies: And becauſe<note n="b" place="margin">Senec. ep.</note> old diſeaſes, and ſo ill manners of men inveterated and habituated, require the more care in their cure: We alſo for the cure of the ſpreading diſeaſe of Banckrupts, will with all care imitate the guiſe of the Egyptian<note n="c" place="margin">Galen 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> epidem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> and Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prieſts; who ſet up notes for the cure of common diſeaſes in publick places.</p>
            <p>Let us then in like manner publiſh holy Antidotes and preſervatives for the cure of Banckrupts diſeaſes, which we wil borrow from the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: For Gods<note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 6.23.</note> Commandement is a Lanthorne, and Inſtruction is a light, and reproofs duely applied are the way of life. They therfore ſhall doe amiſſe, who will be offended with friendly adviſe propounded for to free them from a deadly and old diſeaſe, and to give them Cure and remedie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Banckrupts muſt confeſſe their ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Banckrupts muſt neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſins and offences: Hee that hath fallen off from God and languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth under the burthen of his ſins, ought for a perfect cure of his diſeaſe perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1782:53"/>to turne againe unto his God. Now the firſt ſtep or degree of a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is the confeſſion of his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: He<note n="a" place="margin">Senec. epiſt.</note> that telleth his dreame, may juſtly be concluded to be awake, and he that ſearcheth for his ſins, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth them, may be rightly judged to be in the ready way to recovery: But thou wilt ſay: Indeed I ſhamed not to commit ſinns, but I am aſhamed to confeſſe them. O<note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> incredible folly! art thou not aſhamed of the wound, and art thou aſhamed to have it bound up? Hee that denyeth,<note n="c" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> concealeth, and covereth his vices, maketh them to take deeper root in him; and he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth up the way to his cure, that will not open the cauſe of his diſeaſe to his Phyſitian. Tell mee how will God vouchſafe to pardon that ſinne, which man will not vouchſafe and humble himſelfe to confeſſe? Wherefore<note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.21.</note> for thy Souls good bee not aſhamed to confeſſe the truth: there is a ſhame that bringeth ſinne, and there is a ſhame that bringeth grace and glory. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the concealing and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing ſinne: the Kingly Prophet ſaid;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1782:53"/>
               <hi>When I kept</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 32.3.</note>
               <hi>ſilence, my bones waxed old through my roaring all the day long:</hi> and to encourage us to confeſſion <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>If wee</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 John
4.6.</note> 
               <hi>confeſſe our ſinnes, God is faithfull and juſt to forgive us our ſinnes and to purge us from iniquity.</hi> Thus is Confeſſion Salvation to the Soule and the queller of vices. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not the Banckrupt conceale and hide, but confeſſe and acknowledge his offences.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Banckrupts muſt repent of their ſins and leave them.</note> Secondly, Banckrupts muſt repent of their ſins: for it is not enough for an offendor to confeſſe and lay open his ſins; hee ought alſo to repent and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them; he that repenteth of his ſins is in ſome ſort innocent. Repentance<note n="a" place="margin">Lactant. inſtit.</note> hath not the leaſt place among the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: becauſe it is a correcting of a mans ſelfe; and if when we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned we grieve thereat and confeſſe that we have done amiſſe, and crave pardon of God, hee (ſuch is his mercy) will not deny us pardon, unleſſe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in our ſinnes: Great is the help, great is the comfort of repentance, it is the curing of our wounds and the hope and haven of our ſafety. When
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1782:54"/>
               <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> betooke himſelfe to this har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and confeſſed his ſinnes, he found that God forgave the iniquity thereof: for God is a moſt loving and kinde Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and promiſeth remiſſion<note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 18.21.</note> of ſins to them that repent, and will blot out all their offences, who begin anew to doe juſtice.</p>
            <p>Wherefore O ſinner, put a period to thy naughtineſſe, take a breathing time, conſider well thy caſe, diſpaire not, hope in him whom thou feareſt; fly to him from whom thou runneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, deplore and lament thy wicked life, ſo long as thou liveſt: Turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine<note n="d" place="margin">Anſelm.</note> and repent, leſt thou having bin circumvented by the Divell to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, cheat and beguile others, beeſt cheated and deprived of eternall life, and beeſt adjudged to eternall death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Banckrupts muſt pray for pardon of their ſins.</note> Thirdly, Banckrupts ought daily to pray for remiſſion of their ſinnes, for ſeeing the cry of the Banckrupts evill courſes hath pierced the eares of God, they ought alſo to cry aloud and often to God for pardon of their ſins. Great is the force of prayer: fire<note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> doth not more take away ruſt from iron, than
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1782:54"/>prayer purges the filth of our ſins; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the Banckrupt pray now as heartily and opportunely, as he hath hath ſinned highly and proudly. Let him prepare his heart conſtantly to powre out his ſupplications and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and in the end he ſhall prevaile for pardon. With heart and tongue let him thus ſay. O Lord, though I have loſt my integrity by my ſinne, yet have I not bereaved thee of thy mercy; doe not, O Lord, ſo obſerve the evill of my ſins, as to forget the goodneſſe of thy nature: Be not ſo mindfull of thy juſt anger againſt my guilt, that thou minde not thy loving pitty to poore wretches. True it is, that my guilty conſcience hath deſerved damnation, and my repentance hath not been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſatisfie thee. But ſure it is, that thy mercy is beyond all my ſin: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Jeſus, bee to mee Jeſus and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for thy names ſake; let thy pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be extended to me, while the time of mercy laſteth, leſt I be condemned in the time of Judgment. If thou takeſt me into thy boſome, there will not be leſſe roome for others.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:1782:55"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Banckrupts ought to repay every man his due.</note> Fourthly, Banckrupts ought faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to repay money borrowed; for to the end that a debtor may lift up pure hands and minde to God, aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is very expedient that he pay the whole ſumme borrowed; for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> ſhould owe nothing to any man but love; wherefore<note n="b" place="margin">Senec. B. 5. of benef.</note> he that is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in any kind to another, ought faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to diſcharge the ſame. Hee is<note n="c" place="margin">Senec epiſt.
81.</note> not well-minded that doth more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly borrow, than repay.</p>
            <p>See how <hi>Zacheus</hi> not grudgingly entertained Chriſt at his houſe, yea how willingly he gave ſatisfaction to them, whom he had defrauded, which appeareth not by a bare, but by a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold reſtitution, when Chriſt told him of Salvation come to his houſe: for thus he ſaith, <hi>Behold Lord, if</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>I have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any man by forged cavillation, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store it fourefold.</hi> So it is ſaid of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bael</hi> debtor to <hi>Tobias</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tob. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſight of the writing and ſeale he preſently made pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Gelo</hi> the Tyrant payd the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney borrowed of his ſubjects, as ſoone as the occaſions of his troubles were ended. And <hi>Alexander</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Diod. B. 17</note> 
               <hi>the Great,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:1782:55"/>when <hi>Aſia</hi> was vanquiſhed, out of his owne treaſure paid the debts of his Army to their Creditors. Neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ought the care of a private man to be leſſe for the performance of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and maintaining his Credit by an exact payment of the money which he oweth. Above all a Chriſtian ſhould ſurpaſſe all Pagans and Infidels in care to pay his debts, and maintaine his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by performing his promiſes and Covenants.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Banckrupts muſt avoid ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Fifthly, a care muſt be uſed by Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts in all things to avoid lying: for ſeeing they who reſolve to be rich, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes in their courſes baulk truth, ſure it is that in ſuch ſtraying pathes a Banckrupt alſo walketh: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee is to be admoniſhed to avoid falſhood in his ſpeech, and to think with himſelfe that to<note n="a" place="margin">Cic. Offic. 3.</note> lye, to beguile, to ſupplant others, by cunning to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them for his owne profits ſake, is in no wiſe incident to a good man, and that a fraudulent<note n="b" place="margin">Mich. 6.</note> tongue hath its reſidence only in the mouth of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p>The Perſians and Indians ſo deteſted
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1782:56"/>lying that they put it in the rank of the greateſt Crimes: And enacted a law, that hee<note n="c" place="margin">Alex. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. B. 6 c 10.</note> which deceived his Clyent and thrice abuſed him by lying, ſhould be enjoyned ſilence for all his life time, and ſhould bee uncapable of all magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and honor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> ſo wonderfully hated lying, that hee commanded a lyers tongue to be faſtned to a poſt with three nailes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Apaminondas</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> was ſo ſerious a lover of truth that hee never ſpake a falſe word, no not in jeſt.</p>
            <p>The<note n="f" place="margin">Eraſm. in Adag.</note> 
               <hi>Athenians</hi> forbad lying in markets or places of Commerce: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is never more frequent or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent any where than there; and what doth more become a reaſonable man, than<note n="g" place="margin">Cic. Offic. B. 1.</note> to make uſe of true reaſon and ſpeech, and in all things to have an eye and due regard to truth? And on the contrary it is as unbeſeeming a man to deceive and beguile, as to dote, and not to be himſelfe. Much more ſhould a Chriſtian be of this mind.</p>
            <p>Speech was<note n="h" place="margin">Plat in Tim.</note> given us of God, that mutually we might unfold and declare
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1782:56"/>our mindes one to another, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a good man<note n="i" place="margin">Nigid. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell. 11. B.</note> will avoyd lying, and a prudent man ever tell the truth. Eſpecially as ſaith <hi>Lactantius,</hi> He that<note n="k" place="margin">Of true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip B. 6.</note> is a worſhipper of the true God, ſhould take heed, that hee never bee found to lie with an intent to deceive or wrong others; for it is a foule fault, that he who maketh truth his ſtudy, in any thing ſhould deale falſely, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from that truth which he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to follow after. In this path of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; all vertues there is no place left for lying. Therefore he, who is a true &amp; juſt traveller therein, will not only ſay with
<hi>Lucilius,</hi> a man muſt not lye to his friend and familiar, but further add and reſolve, that no man ought to lye to any other man, no not to one wholy unknowne to him, no not to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or at any time ſuffer his tongue, which ſhould be the interpreter of his heart, to be at variance from his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and thoughts. Every deceiver<note n="l" place="margin">Prov. 11.</note> is an abomination to the Lord; wherfore let us follow the Apoſtles rules, <hi>And lie</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Col. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>not one to another, but laying</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide falſe ſpeaking, utter the truth each
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1782:57"/>man to his neighbour, for we are members of one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. Banckrupts ought to ſhun Covetouſnes.</note> Sixthly, the Banckrupt ought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon all Covetouſneſſe, and to have a lowly minde, and to be well content with his eſtate: for a Covetous pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to bee rich is a great ſpurre and provocation to much injuſtice; they that be ſick of this malady fall into ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and ſnares and into many foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and hurtfull luſts.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> The wages of deceit, which caught <hi>Balaam,</hi> will chaine up theſe men to their confuſion. Let a man be a ſlave to theſe covetous and furious deſires,<note place="margin">Jud. 11.</note> they will drawe him into deſtruction and perdition: for the love<note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10</note> of money is the root of all evill, after which while ſome coveted, they erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves through with many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. Wherefore as much deteſt them as thou wouldeſt the Egyptian theeves,<note n="d" place="margin">Senec. ep. 51.</note> who pretend love and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſtrangers with an intent to ſtrangle them. Let thy deſires<note n="e" place="margin">Idem. epiſt. 11.</note> be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, thence canſt thou not fall. Wee erre<note n="f" place="margin">Horat. carm. 3.</note> in calling him rich who poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth much; that name is better placed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1782:57"/>on him, who wiſely uſeth Gods gifts, and hath skill patiently to beare pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. A man is ſo much the happier, by how much his fardell is ſhorter truſſed up for his journey.</p>
            <p>Why then ſhould any man cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly thirſt after riches? A little<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 37.16.</note> which the righteous hath, is better than great plenty of the wicked: yea better is a little with feare of the Lord, than great treaſure where there is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xation and iniquity: Wherefore<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> let your Converſation be without Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes: for by conquering a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and high ſpirit, you ſhall poſſeſſe a larger Kingdome, than if you ſhould raigne over <hi>Lybia</hi> and the furtheſt parts of the world Northward,<note place="margin">Horat. 2. Carm.</note> and make both India's doe you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. Banckrupts muſt ſhunne perjury, and keep covenant.</note> Seventhly, Banckrupts ought to ſhunne perjurie, and performe their Covenants. For perjury is a ſinne abominated<note n="a" place="margin">Eraſm. de ling.</note> by the heathen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom this ſpeech (I ſwore with my tongue,<note n="b" place="margin">Euripid. in Hippol.</note> my minde is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne) was held moſt wicked and unjuſt; much more ſhould a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1782:58"/>take heed of all manner of perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: Heare how ſome Nations puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it: Among the Indians<note n="c" place="margin">Alex. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. B. 6. c 10.</note> hee who was convicted of perjury, was puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by having his fingers and toes cut off. By the Egyptian lawes perjured men<note n="d" place="margin">Deod. B. 2. Alex. B. 10.</note> had their heads cut off: becauſe they were guilty of a double crime, Firſt, for violating their dutie and faith to God; Secondly, for not holding and obſerving fidelitie with men; which is the greateſt bond of humane ſociety. And even<note n="e" place="margin">Idem Alex.</note> at this day the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane puniſhment is diſgrace and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, the divine puniſhment of perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is deſtruction.</p>
            <p>That men may ſeriouſly avoid both: Let every man eſteeme more his God than his gold, and Godlineſſe than gaine, and ever obſerve faithfull dealing in all his actions.</p>
            <p>The Romans were ſo carefull of their fidelity that they founded a Temple of <hi>Fides</hi> or
<hi>True Dealing</hi> in their Citty, to teach all men to expreſſe faithfulneſs in all their words &amp; deeds. And that fidelity might bee inviolably obſerved by the Romans,
<hi>Numa</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1782:58"/>King conſecrated the right hand to it. Let then Chriſtians take heed of a ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and unconſtant fidelity in their right hand, and to play faſt and looſe at pleaſure in their ſpeeches. Let their breaſts be purged of this filth, that they may be Temples of God glittering and adorned with the reſplendant rayes of faithfulneſſe and truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8. Banckrupts muſt deale juſtly in all their courſes.</note> Eighthly, the Banckrupts ought to obſerve juſt dealing in all their Courſes. It is a moſt undoubted truth, that it is impoſſible intirely<note n="a" place="margin">Tacit. Ann.</note> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve juſt dealing, where a man hath an eye to the greatneſſe of his gaines: Let each man<note n="b" place="margin">Ambroſ. in his Offic.</note> therefore thinke with himſelfe, that a man ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from true dealing, nor wrong or beguile any man thereby to advance his owne eſtate. Heathen <hi>Tully</hi> therefore ſaid well, that the markets and minds of men were both to be purged from<note n="c" place="margin">Orat. for Rabir.</note> all footſteps of wicked and unjuſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And God by <hi>Eſay</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 1.16.</note> biddeth, waſh yee, purifie yee, put away the evill of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe wrong, learne to do good. And <hi>Lanctantius</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">B. Of true worſhip.
6.13.</note> ſaith rightly, It is
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1782:59"/>the chiefe point of a wiſe, juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man to accompt it his riches to deale juſtly. And if any man be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, though he paſſe <hi>Craſſus</hi> or
<hi>Craeſus</hi> in wealth, yet he is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a poore man. And therefore a wiſe man<note n="f" place="margin">Sence. of an hap. life.</note> will let no penny come within his dores, that had not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and juſt entrance.<note place="margin">Stob. Serm. 42.</note> If example will prevaile with us, The Ethiopians, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Macrobians were (and are ſo ſtiled by
<hi>Homer</hi>) moſt holy and moſt juſt. Among the Scythians there are a people,<note place="margin">Caelius antiq. lect. 23.9.</note> whom no man will wrong: becauſe they be held to be ſacred; and whoſoever ſojournes among them, they keep him ſecure from all harmes. The Thuriacks much exerciſed in Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, are free from all craft and deceit. If theſe things were practiſed by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, they ſhould not be neglected and grow into diſuſe among Chriſtians. Eſpecially ſeeing God by his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, when queſtion is made,<note place="margin">Pſal 8.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall dwell in in thy holy mountaine and reſt in thy holy hill?</hi> Anſwereth: <hi>Even he that walketh uprightly and worketh righteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:1782:59"/>
            <p>A Banckrupt muſt ninthly avoid hypocriſie, and be truly vertuous.<note place="margin">9. Banckrupts muſt be truly vertuous and avoid hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifie.</note> 
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernard</hi> complained<note n="a" place="margin">Bern. on Cant. Serm. 602.</note> that in his dayes the filthie contagion of hypocriſie ſpread it ſelfe into many mens minds and became the more dangerous and deſperate, by how much it was more common; becauſe connived at. The beſt Counſell and moſt compendious way to root out this miſchiefe, is to ſtrive for a ſerious and true perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of each mans dutie; for as the light<note n="b" place="margin">Cic. 2. de finibus.</note> of the Sun makes the light of the Candle ſeeme nothing, and quite extinguiſheth the pleaſure and benefit which we tooke in it: ſo the ſplendor and nobleneſſe of true vertue will Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe and darken the eſteeme of all outward things and the covetous deſire thereof. Vertue and true godlineſſe maketh men truly noble, and entitles them good men. Therefore, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wild<note n="c" place="margin">Horac. Epod.</note> and fruitleſſe boughes ſpring in thy heart, prune them off, and graft better fruit thereon, even the fruit of true vertue, which is the peculiar good belonging to mankinde, expecially to a Chriſtian man, who beareth about in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1782:60"/>him the Image of his God, and is never more mindfull of the Name of God, than when hee is not onely an hearer of Gods Word, but really and indeed a practiſer of the ſame. And a Chriſtian man is a living Temple of God, and is not ſo much to be adomed with gold and the corruptible ſplendor of pearles and precious ſtones,<note place="margin">Lanctant. Inſtit.
5.8.</note> as with everlaſting and glorious ornaments of true vertue and an holy life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10. Coſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell muſt be avoided.</note> Tenthly, ſuch as would not bee Banckrupts, muſt abſtaine from ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuous expences, and namely from too coſtly apparell: for if needleſſe and too ſumptuous outward omaments ſpend mens eſtates, Banckrupts muſt ſhunne expence herein. For as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, all goodneſſe and vertue is extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the fickle unconſtancy and too great nicety of adorning the body.
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Atheneus B. 12.</note> having conquered the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, left the modeſt Grecian habit for the effeminate Perſick Garbe, whence the more noble Macedonian ſpirits deemed not the Perſians ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Grecians Armes, as the Grecians triumphed over by the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1782:64"/>delicacies. And in theſe times out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh and ſtrange attire is ſo ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hunted after, that other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes may ſeeme to have triumphed over us and put their faſhions upon us. Yea, ſuch is our folly herein, that not that faſhion is pleaſing to our humors, which is moſt convenient, expedient, and uſefull, but that which is laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, though it be moſt vaine and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick: not that which beſt preſerves from cold, and is moſt for our health, but that moſt ſets forth our riotous fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. A glorious and pompous oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is more regarded than a ſeemely and decent moderation. Let men of this humor know, that theſe things cannot paſſe without Gods juſt indignation. For God will viſit<note n="b" place="margin">Sophon.</note> all them that are clothed with ſtrange apparell. Were not riotouſneſſe in Apparell and<note n="c" place="margin">Greg. homil. 6. on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</note> gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry a fault juſtly to be blamed: God would never have ſet forth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> in his rough garment: Nor would the Apoſtle have taught women not to delight in preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and coſtly garments, but to cloth themſelves as became women profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1782:65"/>religion, and expreſſing it by good works. Nor would the Goſpell have ſpoken of a rich man clothed in ſilk and purple every day. Thoſe things,<note n="d" place="margin">Epictet.</note> which we uſe about our bodies, are for our ſouls ſake, and for lifes preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as meate, drink, clothing, houſes, attendants: whatſoever therein ſerveth for ſuperfluous oſtentation and delicacie is to be rejected. A cleanlyneſſe, not womaniſh or odious,<note place="margin">Tully Offic.</note> but ſuch as may free us from Clowniſh &amp; uncivill neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of our ſelves, doth beſt become us. As in moſt things elſe, ſo in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, a meane is beſt. Beſides there is a clothing more pretious and honorable than golden Tiſhew, and all outward bravery: And that is the putting<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 4.24. Zanch. ep. to Q. Eliz.</note> on of Jeſus Chriſt: Here is the true <hi rend="sup">g</hi> and moſt comely garment of all; to obtaine which, each man ſhould imploy his beſt care, and ſtrive to put off the old man with his actions, and to put on the new, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: This garment, he that is a profeſſor of the true faith, will put on, that he may appeare beautifull and gratious in the cyes of the moſt High.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:1782:60"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">11. Stately building is to be avoyded. Horat. Carm. 2.</note> Eleventhly, hee that would avoid impoveriſhing of himſelfe and being Banckrupt, muſt not build for his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe ſtately houſes and magnificent pallaces; ſuch as his own ground will not ſuſteyne, without extending their foundation into his neighbors and Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents bounds, nor his eſtate maintaine without borrowing. Such builders commonly forget their Sepulchers, and ſet their debts fartheſt off from their thoughts; yea they<note n="b" place="margin">Saluſt.</note> make all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more worthy to be ſeene than themſelves, and take great care to have their buildings an honor to themſelves &amp; themſelves a diſgrace to their build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I wiſh that ſuch as theſe are, would conſider truly, what is to be thought of brave buildings: Are they not meere ſhewes, vanities, bubbles? <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> built him royall houſes, prepared gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and orchards: So that hee was great and increaſed in all things beyond all that were before him: But when hee had thus denyed his eyes nothing which might content him, and had conſidered with himſelfe, and juſtly judged of the works of his hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1782:61"/>all were but meere vanity and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of Spirit.<note place="margin">B. 1. of true worſhip.</note> For (as ſaith <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>) they are ſoone either ruinated by a ſudden earth-quake, or conſumed by fire, or taken away by enemies inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or moulder away in time. For there is nothing erected by humane art &amp; induſtry, which time doth not waſte and conſume. Why then e ſhould man let his mind wander after vaine things? This made the Heathen<note n="f" place="margin">Cic. Offic. 1.</note> Orator to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort from ſumptuous and magnificent buildings, and to require a meane and meaſure as in the whole courſe of mans life, ſo eſpecially in building. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let a<note n="g" place="margin">Epiſt. 7.</note> man weigh all things duely, and he will, as <hi>Seneca</hi> adviſeth, think meanely of all ornaments and glorious ſuperfluities, which the needleſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of man produceth, and count no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wounderfull, but the ſoule which being of greateſt worth of all things in this world, can here finde nothing greater than it ſelfe. Beſides let a man<note n="h" place="margin">Cicero.</note> look upwards and behold the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pallace and manſion above, then can he not ſet his care, or fix his hope and truſt on buildings, lands, or any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1782:61"/>mane thing, which the common ſort of men ſo much applaudeth. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſacred ſcripture telleth us of an houſe<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> and building not made with hands, but eternall in the heavens, where is all perfection of bliſſe and happineſſe. So that it cannot otherwiſe be, but that thou ſhouldſt diſeſteeme thy roomes ſet out with marble and pretious ſtones,<note place="margin">Cyprian Epiſt. to Donat.</note> and the vaulted roofe glittering with gold, when thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreſt, that God hath prepared for thee an heavenly houſe, in which hee himſelfe abides as the Temple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">12. Riotous and ſumptuous banqueting is to be avoyded.</note> In the twelfth place riotouſneſſe and ſumptuous banquetting is to be avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And why ſhould a man laviſh out his wealth in prodigious and prodigall banquets? Why ſhould he ſeek for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates from all parts, and never think his table ſufficiently decked and a dorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?<note place="margin">Tacit. hiſt. 4. Sence. col. 95.</note> In old time men contended to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell one another in vertue and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and now will they outvie each other in wanton and needleſte riot, in curious dainties, and night-revellings and banquets? Is all frugality ſo baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that men<note n="b" place="margin">Idem.</note> are not contented to glut
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1782:62"/>their teeth, pallates, ſtomacks and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, but have gluttonous eyes, not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied? did they but conſider<note n="c" place="margin">Cic. Offic. 1.</note> what is the excellency and dignity of man, they could not but conceive, how baſe and beaſtly a thing it is to run out into a riotous delicious and wanton courſe of life, and how commendable it is to live ſparingly, continently, gravely, ſoberly. Surely<note n="d" place="margin">Senec. ep
65.</note> man is a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent creature and borne to higher mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, than that hee ſhould become a drudge to his body. And ſhall hee<note n="e" place="margin">Cicer. parad.</note>, when God hath given him a ſoule, than which nothing is more excellent and divine, ſo abaſe and vilify himſelfe, that hee ſhall make no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene himſelfe and a beaſt? Let him rather think,<note place="margin">Alex of Alex, B. 3. c 11.</note> what becometh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments given him by God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void rare, new invented delicates, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized and ſumptuous diſhes, exquiſite ſawces and provocatives of gluttony. If any pretend that different times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire different manners: I wiſh that<note n="g" place="margin">Plaut. in Trin.</note> old and frugall courſe of frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſobriety might rather doe man honor, and maintaine his ſtrength and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1782:62"/>hardnes, and fit him for vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than new and worſe courſe and manners make him contemptible, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate, and unfit for any worthy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. But ſome will ſay, cuſtome hath prevayled, and if there be a fault of that kind among men, it is not at all diſcerned: becauſe it is growne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>St</hi> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> anſwers this,<note place="margin">Greg. c. 10. in the decrees.</note> ſaying that cuſtome is not to be of force to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any man to ſinne; An evill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome as an evill humor or diſeaſe in the body, is to be purged out and quite extinguiſhed: leſt wicked men ſhould draw it up by degrees into a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Let a pious Chriſtian rather learne how little ſerveth to maintaine a ſober and religious life, and what moderation contenteth and beſt fitteth nature, and ſo ſhall his minde be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt exceſſe, and taken off from from all allurements to pleaſure and deliciouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">13. The Banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void pleaſure.</note> The Banckrupt in the thirteenth place to ſhunne all exceſſe of pleaſure and to bridle all exorbit and deſires, and free his minde from all pernitious and voluptuous incitations to evill: Let
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1782:63"/>him give care to the Apoſtle, who ſaith, <hi>Beloved</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you as ſtrangers and pilgrims, abſtaine from freſhly luſts which fight againſt the ſoule.</hi> 'Tis a high point<note n="b" place="margin">Hieronym. Epiſt.</note> of vertue for men that carry fleſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, not to live according to the fleſh, but to watch this enemie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and carried about in them, with
<hi>Argus</hi> hundred eyes; that the ſoule and better part become not ſlave to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and worſe part of man. Man hath a continuall warfare to exerciſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in: hee is never at quiet; diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of pleaſures doe ſtill and ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade him; what a carefull watch, what ſcouts &amp; centinels, what ſtrong bands are to be prepared for the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and overcoming ſo ſubtle, perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Lactant.</note> and mortall a foe. Suppoſe wee that theſe things be ſo, though the fight be dangerous, yet is the victory glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which hee ſhall obtaine who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth and quelleth his unruly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, baniſheth poyſonous pleaſures, warreth againſt all beaſtly luſts, and endevoureth to compoſe his life after the rule preſcribed by the divine and ſacred lawes. And this ſhall any man
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1782:63"/>more eaſily doe, if he conſider with what endleſſe paine &amp; intolerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a ſhort and ſmall pleaſure is bought. If any ſay, I finde corruption ſo ſtrong in me that I cannot abandon and caſt off pleaſures which inſinuate themſelves into my heart moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. To him I anſwer:<note place="margin">Horat. B. 1. ep.</note> This ſoftneſſe and eaſineſſe of minde is to be rejected, and manly courage put on; the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to be tamed and chained up: for unleſſe they be maſtered and made to obey, they will domineere and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.2.</note> A care therefore muſt be had that ſinne raigne not in our mortall bodies to make us obey it in the luſts thereof: So ſhall the ſwelling, proud and unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly motions of mens minds (though become unbridled and wild by proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſucceſſe, and laſhing out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bonds of reaſon and right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding) be crubbed and made obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to reaſon and temperance: So that the Soule ſhall more ſafely ſit as Queene, and ruling more eaſily the quelled affections (which otherwiſe would draw men from obedience to Gods Law and reaſons direction) more
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1782:64"/>ſeriouſly and earneſtly imploy it ſelfe in the duties of piety and equity, and for ever here raigne over inordinate luſts &amp; pleaſures, till at length it raigne in heaven with Chriſt, &amp; be freed from the leaſt moleſtation and feare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Thus farre have I proceeded to open the remedies of Banckrupts courſes, &amp; in breife have ſet down, what I judged moſt profitable, uſefull and effectuall. My wiſh and deſire is; that my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell may prove as pleaſing, as it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; and may not only delight, but Cure: which it will doe, if it pierce not the eares of men onely, but the hearts too; And be not ſufferd there to lye fruitleſſe, as ſeed lying on the top of the ground, which dryeth, wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and cometh to nought; but take deep root in the bottome of mens hearts, and by the rayes of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhining thereon, prove moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. They whoſe bodies are waſted &amp; weakned by a lingring diſeaſe long growing by degrees upon them, muſt be cured by a continuall courſe of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and by dayly evacuations and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1782:65"/>be brought to a due te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per againe: So the ſickneſſe of mens minds and harmfull maladies long rooted therein, cannot poſſibly be cured, unleſſe the Phyſick here preſcribed bee faithfully obſerved, and frequently and dayly uſed, and the due circumſtances of the precepts &amp; directions for the planting of vertue and extirpating of evill, moſt conſcionably put in practiſe: which that it may truly and indeed bee done and effected, I humbly and heartily beſeech God the ſoveraigne ruler of all to grant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur, </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohannes Hanſly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
